Brahma Bhairavaya Namah Brahma Bhairavaya Namah
ब्रह्म भैरवाय नमः ब्रह्म भैरवाय नमः
Connections have increased in the last three months
पिछले तीन महीनों में कनेक्शन बढ़ चुके
Are. It is visible. See, life never
हैं। दिख रहा है। देखिए जीवन कभी भी ना
It does not move linearly. in the life of a human being
लीनियर नहीं चलता है। इंसान के जीवन में
This is Garuda Yoga. Garuda dies and
ये गरुड़ योग आता है। गरुड़ मर जाता है और
He becomes alive again. that you are of perfect height
फिर से वो जीवित होता है। कि आप एकदम हाइट
I will stay in after that I will fall after that again
में रहेंगे उसके बाद गिरेंगे उसके बाद फिर
Will rise from. These who will rise a second time
से उठेंगे। ये जो दूसरी बार उठेंगे फिर
Don't fall. I get lost a lot. Any
गिरना नहीं। मैं खो जाता हूं ज्यादा। किसी
You are also worshipping that god. a time like this
भी देवता को आप पूज रहे हैं। एक समय ऐसा
comes you can feel that god
आता है कि आप फील कर सकते हैं कि देवता
You are coming with us. Brother when mom looks at me
हमारे साथ चल रहे हैं। भाई जब मम्मी नजर
Does it take off or is anyone taking your sight away?
उतारती है या कोई भी आपकी नजर उतली हो रहा
what would have happened
क्या होता
Is? These ten Mahavidyas in a person's life
है? एक इंसान के जीवन में ये दश महाविद्या
What is the role of? in tantra way
का रोल क्या रहता है? तंत्र मार्ग में ऐसा
It is said that if you do sadhna of Bhagwati Tara
बोलते हैं कि भगवती तारा का अगर आप साधना
If they do, Mahadev comes running after them
करते हैं ना तो महादेव पीछे दौड़े चले आते
Are. Do you believe that in one family
हैं। आप ये मानते हो कि एक ही फैमिली में
You are reborn. It could be this
आपका पुनर्जन्म होता है। हो सकता है ये
It happens. may be some other soul but the story
होता है। मे बी सम अदर आत्मा बट द स्टोरी
Remains the same. How has Sanatan Dharma progressed for centuries?
रिमेन सेम। सदियों से सनातन धर्म आगे कैसे
increased? Because we are never finished
बढ़ा? क्योंकि हम लोग कभी खत्म ही नहीं
happened. even when the end of mankind comes
हुए। जब मनुष्यों का अंत होता है ना तब भी
gods live
देवता रहते
Are. Very deep spiritual conversation
हैं। बहुत ही गहरी स्पिरिचुअल कन्वर्सेशन
Is. The title of the last episode was Bhoot Vs.
है। पिछले एपिसोड का टाइटल था भूत वर्सेस
Bhairava. There was talk of horror, talk of Tantra
भैरव। हॉरर की बातें हुई, तंत्र की बातें
Hui. But in today's episode it's not very deep.
हुई। पर आज के एपिसोड में ना बहुत ही गहरी
Spiritual things have happened. If Sanatana Dharma
स्पिरिचुअल बातें हुई हैं। अगर सनातन धर्म
The Tantric secrets of Sanatan Dharma
के तांत्रिक रहस्यों को सनातन धर्म के
Tantric secrets and Sanatan Dharma
तांत्रिक सीक्रेट्स को और सनातन धर्म के
If you want to identify a Tantric medium then
तांत्रिक माध्यम को पहचानना चाहते हो तो
Watch this episode till the end. maybe one day
यह वाला एपिसोड एंड तक देखिए। शायद एक दिन
The world of podcasts will not exist. Any
पडकास्ट की दुनिया रहेगी नहीं। कोई
Won't listen to podcasts. But even then it is not like that
पॉडकास्ट सुनेगा नहीं। बट तब भी ना ऐसे जो
These are spiritual episodes that bother people a lot
स्पिरिचुअल एपिसोड्स हैं ये लोगों को बहुत
I will teach you something. Guide people too much
कुछ सिखाएंगे। लोगों को बहुत ज्यादा गाइड
We will do it because of people like Shishir Kumar.
करेंगे शिशिर कुमार जैसे लोगों की वजह से।
don't want to say too much about him other than
डोंट वांट टू से टू मच अबाउट हिम अदर देन
the fact that this is not one of my favourites
द फैक्ट कि यार यह ना वन ऑफ़ माय फेवरेट
Guests are to speak to learn from.
गेस्ट हैं टू स्पीक टू टू लर्न फ्रॉम।
Enjoy today's episode. Many more
एंजॉय कीजिए आज का एपिसोड। बहुत सारी
There have been talks about Sanatan Dharma,
बातें हुई है सनातन धर्म को लेकर,
About spirituality and about life.
स्पिरिचुअलिटी को लेकर और जिंदगी को लेकर।
Watch it till the end.
वाच इट टिल दी एंड।
[music]
[संगीत]
Shishir sir has returned. Bhram Bhairavaya Namah
शिशिर सर लौट चुके हैं। भ्रम भैरवाय नमः
Bhram Bhairavaya Namah Thank you for being in the
भ्रम भैरवाय नमः थैंक यू फॉर बीइंग इन द
Studio again sir. Thank you to us too
स्टूडियो अगेन सर। आपका भी धन्यवाद हमें
To call. How are you? I am fine.
बुलाने के लिए। कैसे हो? मैं कुशल हूं।
Where to start? where last time
कहां से स्टार्ट करें? जहां पिछली बार
Bhairav ​​had left it. ok or ten mahavidya bhagavati
छोड़ा था भैरव। ओके या दश महाविद्या भगवती
Where you start from. ok maybe from bhairav
जहां से आप शुरू करो। ओके शायद भैरव से
Let's start. Ok. Whatever this happened
स्टार्ट करते हैं। ठीक है। यह जो भी हुआ
What do you think about the past three months?
पिछले तीन महीनों में आपके नजरिए से क्या
Was? because i remember the first or the second
था? क्योंकि मुझे याद है पहले या दूसरे
I received a message from you the other day. you said that
दिन आपकी एक मैसेज आई थी हम। आपने कहा कि
Bhairav ​​ji is with you. Basically you did this
भैरव जी आपके साथ हैं। बेसिकली आपने ये
Said. hum hum to would just like to know
कहा था। हम हम तो वुड जस्ट लाइक टू नो
Because I haven't talked to you outside.
क्योंकि मैंने आपसे बाहर बात नहीं करी है।
Now when you were sitting in front of me for 10-15 minutes
अब जब आप मेरे सामने बैठे थे 10-15 मिनट
I did not talk about it then. So tell me now. When
के लिए तब बात नहीं करी। तो अब बताइए। जब
You are in sadhana when you are a seeker
आप साधना में होते हैं ना जब आप साधक होते
If you are, then two things happen in your life.
हैं तो दो चीजें आपके जीवन में होती हैं।
One is a power in your life which
एक तो आपके जीवन में एक शक्तियां जो होती
Isn't it, she is always there? Are you a seeker or
है ना वह हमेशा रहती हैं। आप साधक हो या
No it is not so. it has some powers
नहीं हो। उसमें कुछ ऐसी शक्तियां होती हैं
which is negative. Ok? but he
जो नकारात्मक होती है। ठीक है? लेकिन वह
It lives with you as a parasite and
आपके साथ पैरासाइट बनकर रहती है और आपको
It brings benefits. When you begin to meditate
लाभ पहुंचाती है। जब आप साधना शुरू करते
If yes, then remove these powers from your life.
हैं तो इन शक्तियों को आपके जीवन से जाना
Does matter. So he creates all kinds of intrigues
पड़ता है। तो वह हर तरीके का प्रपंच रचता
that you feel that the gods and the
है कि आपको ऐसा लगे कि जो देवता हैं और जो
This is sadhana, both of these are wrong for us. And
साधना है यह दोनों हमारे लिए गलत है। और
will bring you into such a situation that you
आपको ऐसे सिचुएशन में ला देगा कि आप
One should completely turn away from the practice. just like that
बिल्कुल ही साधना से विमुख हो जाए। ऐसा ही
Something happened to you. But you stood firm and
कुछ आपके साथ हुआ। लेकिन आप अडिग रहे और
If you trusted in Sadhana and God then God
साधना और देवता पर भरोसा किया तो देवता ने
Whatever Mahamaya's deception was to you
आपको जो भी महामाया का जो एक प्रपंच था
Kicked him out. This is a topic.
उससे बाहर निकाल दिया। ये एक विषय है।
Second is that in sadhana you have to learn
दूसरा है कि साधना में आपको सीखना होता
Is. then you won't make mistakes and you will learn
है। तो आप गलती नहीं करेंगे तो सीखेंगे
How? Everybody makes mistakes and
कैसे? हर एक व्यक्ति गलती करता है और गलती
Mahamaya makes it happen. and you have a little
महामाया कराती है। और आपने तो छोटी सी
I made a mistake. It was your narrator's mistake, who said
गलती की। आपका तो वाचक गलती था ना जो बोल
Do people make personnel mistakes?
के किया लोगों से कार्मिक गलतियां हो जाती
This is what we do. Ok? I have a
है जो कर करते हैं हम। ठीक है? मैंने एक
Read about the topic recently. That
टॉपिक के बारे में हाल ही में पढ़ा। उस
The name of the topic is Ego Death. we we are one
टॉपिक का नाम है ईगो डेथ। हम हम अ एक
It is an English word. Ego means self
इंग्लिश शब्द है। ईगो मतलब सेल्फ
Identification of who I am, what am I?
आइडेंटिफिकेशन कि मैं हम हम मैं क्या हूं?
Who am I? What have I done?
मैं कौन हूं? मैंने क्या-क्या किया है?
What can I do? We think of all that
मैं क्या कर सकता हूं? हम वो सारे सोच
He passed away. we their death we
उनकी डेथ हो गई। हम उनकी मृत्यु हो गई हम
My ego died especially in that one week
ईगो डेथ हो गई उस एक हफ्ते में एस्पेशली
which was the first week we we because
जो पहले वाला एक हफ्ता था हम हम क्योंकि
We were threatened with violence in our childhood
वायलेंस के थ्रेट्स थे हम अ बचपन में
I think I read a couplet by Kabir
मैंने आई थिंक कबीर का एक दोहा पढ़ा था
Where basically they say that the one above
जहां बेसिकली अ वो कहते हैं कि ऊपर वाले
has so much power that he can put pressure on you
के पास इतना ज्यादा पावर है कि वो आपके सर
One can cause your ego death by pulling a hair from
से एक बाल खींच कर आपकी ईगो डेथ करा सकता
Is. It can bring an earthquake into your life.
है। आपके जिंदगी में एक भूकंप ला सकता है।
That is why it is very important to be humble and polite
इसलिए हंबल रहना, विनम्र रहना बहुत जरूरी
Is. I just remembered that couplet that friend
है। बस उस दोहे की याद आई थी कि यार
Everything was fine three-four days ago. then this
तीन-चार दिन पहले सब ठीक ही था। फिर ये
There was an earthquake. See, life never
भूकंप हो गया। देखिए जीवन कभी भी ना
It does not move linearly. go in the flow like this
लीनियर नहीं चलता है। धार में चले ऐसा
Does not happen. and if your life is a torrent
नहीं होता है। और अगर आपका जीवन एक धार
If I follow you will neither be able to learn anything nor
में चलेगा तो ना आप कुछ सीख पाएंगे और ना
There will be happiness in life. Until and Unless You
जीवन में आनंद रहेगा। अंटिल एंड अनलेस यू
have
हैव
Challenges till then you have this courage to live
चैलेंजेस तब तक आपको यह जीने का जो एक
The purpose is that it ends. If suppose
मकसद है ना वह खत्म हो जाता है। अगर सपोज
linear running you are enjoying life bus
लीनियर चल रहा है यू आर एंजॉयंग लाइफ बस
It is going on, it is going on. Come on look at you seeker
चल रहा है चल रहा है। चल देखो आपने साधक
I talked about this and not about what happens in the life of a seeker
की बात की ना कि साधक के जीवन में क्या
It happens? Why does it happen so quickly? As
होता है? क्यों इतना जल्दी होता है? जैसे
A normal person who sells groceries
एक नॉर्मल इंसान है ना जो एक परचून की
does the shop. He goes in the morning and evening
दुकान करता है। वो सुबह जाता है और शाम
I close the shop and have a family
में दुकान बंद करता है और उसका एक फैमिली
Life goes on. there is something very much in it
लाइफ चलता है। उसमें कुछ बहुत ज्यादा कुछ
It doesn't happen. If there is a lot of it in the house,
नहीं होता। उसमें वो बहुत होगा तो घर में
There will be some fights but that is the life which
कुछ लड़ाईयां हो जाएंगी लेकिन वो जीवन जिस
begins his life the way he ends it
तरीके से शुरू करता है उसका जीवन समाप्त
It happens. When a seeker lives his life
हो जाता है। जब एक साधक अपना जीवन जीता है
Neither does he start acquiring knowledge.
ना तो वो विद्याओं को ग्रहण करने लगता है।
Ok? And when you acquire knowledge,
ठीक है? और जब आप विद्याओं को ग्रहण कर
If you are learning then it is according to your nature
रहे हैं तो विद्या जो है वह अपने नेचर के
It comes as per calculation. When your knowledge gradually
हिसाब से आती है। आपका धीरे-धीरे जब ज्ञान
When the eye opens then there are ten great scholars
चक्षु खुलता है ना तो दश महाविद जो है ना
He starts showing you his different side.
वो अपना अलग-अलग रूप आपको दिखाना शुरू
She does. You start with black
करती है। आप शुरू करते हैं काली से
The great void remains. you give me some ideas
महाशून्य रहते हैं। आप आपको कुछ आईडिया
Not there. But you have it all inside you. To you
नहीं है। लेकिन आप आपके अंदर सब है। आपको
I don't know anything. then the second stage knowledge
कुछ पता नहीं है। फिर दूसरा स्टेज ज्ञान
It comes in which Tara comes. Tara to you
का आता है जिसमें तारा आती हैं। तारा आपको
It gives knowledge. Ok? The third stage comes
ज्ञान देती हैं। ठीक है? तीसरा स्टेज आता
It is of Tripura Sundari. Tripura Sundari who
है त्रिपुर सुंदरी का। त्रिपुर सुंदरी जो
Yes, it develops the brain. Fourth Stage
है वो ब्रेन डेवलप करती है। चौथा स्टेज
Bhuvaneshwari's comes. Bhuvaneshwari arrives
आता है भुवनेश्वरी का। भुवनेश्वरी आती है
So it gives wealth. Then Bhairavi comes
तो ऐश्वर्य देती है। फिर भैरवी आती है तो
What is Bhairavi? She destroys enemies
भैरवी क्या है? वो दुश्मनों का नाश करती
It is around you. So you become supreme.
है आपके आसपास का। सो यू बिकम सुप्रीम।
After that which rotates in a sequential manner
उसके बाद जो क्रमबद्ध तरीके से धुमावती
comes and this goddess who comes, Banglamukhi
आती है और यह जो देवी आती है, बंगलामुखी
Here comes, they are goddesses of destruction. So
आती हैं, दे आर गॉडेस ऑफ डिस्ट्रक्शन। सो
All the empires that you have built will be lost
ऑल द एंपायर्स दैट यू हैव बिल्ड वो फिर
One by one they collapse. And finally
एक-एक करके ध्वस्त होता है। और अंत में
Who is coming? Kamala, great glory, great knowledge.
कौन आती है? कमला, महाश्वर्य, महाज्ञान।
Ok? So these are the stages which are 10 Mahavidya
ठीक है? तो दीज़ आर द स्टेजेस जो 10 महाविद
It happens to a seeker's life 10
होता है ना वो साधक का जीवन का 10
This is Mahavidya. Meaning, if you practice
महाविद्या है। मतलब अगर आपने साधना
If you start, a timeline will also start
स्टार्ट करी तो एक टाइमलाइन भी स्टार्ट हो
goes. A timeline starts with you
जाता है। एक टाइमलाइन आपके साथ स्टार्ट हो
goes. And you see, the order is 10
जाता है। और आप देखना वो जो क्रम है ना 10
Maha Vidya which is written in a sequence
महाविद्या जो एक क्रम में लिखा जाता है ना
that after Kali, Tara and then Tripura Sundari
कि काली के बाद तारा फिर त्रिपुरा सुंदरी
then Bhuvaneshwari then Tripura Bhairavi and finally
फिर भुवनेश्वरी फिर त्रिपुरा भैरवी और अंत
The order in which Lakshmi comes is not like this
में जो लक्ष्मी आती हैं यह क्रम ऐसे नहीं
It has been written. this is the order it is exactly
लिखा गया है। यह क्रम जो है यह बिल्कुल ही
It happens according to the life of the seeker. And
साधक के जीवन के हिसाब से होता है। और
what is in your life right now what does it say
आपके जीवन में जो है अभी क्या कहते हैं जो
If you are around the fifth Mahavidya then you
पांचवी महाविद्या के आसपास आप हैं तो आपको
You too will definitely be cured. Your
बिल्कुल ही आपको भी ठीक किया जाएगा। आपके
the people around will also be cured so that
आसपास के लोगों को भी ठीक किया जाएगा ताकि
the costume of a seeker which is a costume
एक साधक का जो एक वेशभूषा है जो वेशभूषा
I mean it's not clothes, it's the eternal gown
मतलब कपड़े नहीं वो जो एटरनल एक गाउन है
When you wear it, Mahalakshmi is with you
वो आप जब धारण करते हैं जब महालक्ष्मी आप
If it comes, are you ready for it?
पे आ जाती है ना तो उसके लिए आप तैयार हो
Let's go, okay, see, there is God too
जाएं ठीक है देखिए देवता भी जो है ना
Even gods are not free from mistakes.
देवता भी गलतियों से बचे हुए नहीं है।
All gods make mistakes. so that like Maya
सारे देवता गलती करते हैं। ताकि माया जैसे
I just told you about Bhagwati. Each and every goddess
अभी मैंने भगवती का बताया। हर एक देवी
You will find such a story of God
देवता को का आपको एक ऐसा कहानी मिल जाएगा
In which mistakes were made. Lord Dattatreya
जिसमें कि गलतियां हुई। दत्तात्रेय भगवान
came into being because Lakshmi ji,
का प्रादुर्भाव हुआ क्योंकि लक्ष्मी जी,
Parvati ji and Saraswati ji the three that you
पार्वती जी और सरस्वती जी तीनों जो आपने
When I talked about ego, his ego came to the fore
ईगो की बात की ना उनका ईगो सामने आ गया
Was. Anusuya was so chaste that she used to hide her clothes
था। अनुसूया इतनी सती थी कि वो अपने कपड़े
I did not bring water. so much their power
में ना पानी ले आती थी। इतना उनका पावर
Was. So he said to Mahadev, Vishnu
था। तो उन्होंने बोला महादेव को, विष्णु
to Ji and to Brahma ji that you people should go and
जी को और ब्रह्मा जी को कि आप लोग जाकर के
By breaking the sanctity of Anusuya
अनुसूया का जो यह पवित्रता है इसको भंग कर
Give it. So then they went to Anusuya.
दीजिए। तो फिर वो लोग अनुसूया के पास गए।
Then Anusuya kept him as her child.
फिर अनुसूया ने उनको अपना बच्चा बना के रख
Took it. And then don’t leave them. So
लिया। और फिर उनको छोड़े ही ना। तो
The entire balance of the universe is disturbed
ब्रह्मांड का पूरा बैलेंस जो है वह खराब
Done. Then the goddess had to come to Anusuya
हो गया। फिर भगवतियों को आना पड़ा अनुसूया
Near. I apologized for the ego death you caused
के पास। माफ़ी मांगा जो ईगो डेथ की आपने
and then the universe started moving the same way
बात की और फिर ब्रह्मांड वैसे ही चलने
Put. Is it okay? So you will get many such
लगा। ठीक है ना? तो ऐसे आपको अनेक
You will get examples. so you can't live in the
एग्जांपल मिलेंगे। सो यू कैन नॉट लिव इन द
Remotes that you did something. the point is you
रिमोट्स दैट यू डिड समथिंग। द पॉइंट इज यू
You have learned and you should move on. Increased connection
हैव लर्न एंड यू शुड मूव ऑन। कनेक्शन बढ़
have been done. Yes. That is visible. right now means
चुके हैं। हां। वो दिख रहा है। अभी मतलब
Sadhana is happening with even more devotion
साधना और भी ज्यादा भक्ति के साथ हो रही
Is. And even now it is happening with devotion
है। और अब तक भी भक्ति के साथ ही हो रही
Was. Butt devotion on steroids. he started to be
थी। बट भक्ति ऑन स्टेरॉइड्स। वो होने लगा
Is. That I get lost in meditation. and I
है। कि मैं खो जाता हूं साधना में। एंड आई
have realized that that is the right way to do it
हैव रियलाइज दैट दैट इज द राइट वे टू डू
Sadhana. we we are absolutely. I with my
साधना। हम हम बिल्कुल है। मैं अपने जो साथ
I tell people who are learning
लोग हैं जो सीखते हैं उनको मैं बोलता हूं
that if you want to see Bhagwati, Bhairava
कि अगर आपको भगवती का दर्शन करना है, भैरव
Do you want to have darshan of Lord Shiva or any other deity?
जी का दर्शन करना है या किसी भी देवता को
You are worshipping. until madness sets in
आप पूज रहे हैं। जब तक पागलपन नहीं आएगा
Till then if you tie yourself to anything
ना तब तक आप अगर किसी चीज में खुद को बांध
have been. Whether it be an action, whether it be
रहे हैं। वो चाहे वह क्रिया हो, चाहे वह
Be it a garland. Ok? until you are in those things
माला हो। ठीक है? तब तक आप उन चीजों में
Will remain stranded. when you get out of them
फंसे रहेंगे। जब उनसे आप बाहर निकलते हैं
Only then you are able to pave the way for devotion
तभी आप भक्ति मार्ग में प्रशस्त होते हैं
And the god takes one look and says yes this too
और देवता का एक नजर जाता है कि हां यह भी
Any
कोई
Is.
है।
One change I have adopted is this
एक चेंज को मैंने अडॉप्ट किया है वो ये है
That means suppose I sit down to meditate
कि मतलब मान लो अगर मैं साधना करने बैठा
I sit in the morning. in the afternoon or evening
हूं मैं सुबह बैठता हूं। दोपहर या शाम को
I sit and then I sit at night. But
बैठता हूं और फिर रात में बैठता हूं। बट
In those three ah time periods if I
उन तीनों अह टाइम पीरियड में अगर मुझे
If I am not feeling the feeling of devotion then I get up
भक्ति का भाव नहीं फील हो रहा तो मैं उठ
I go from there. do it right and during the day
जाता हूं वहां से। सही करते और दिन में
You may feel it in one of the three time periods
तीन टाइम पीरियड में से एक में तो फील हो
it goes away at least at night but we are devoted
ही जाता है एटलीस्ट रात में हम बट भक्ति
I do not sit down to do sadhana without it. Sadhana
के बिना साधना करने नहीं बैठता हूं। साधना
walking with you on the path when you and
मार्ग में आपके साथ आगे चल के जब आप और
If you do sadhna then it will also happen that you will get many
साधना करेंगे तो ऐसा भी होगा कि आपको कई
You won't feel like doing sadhana for days.
दिनों तक साधना करने की इच्छा नहीं होगी।
Meaning, you will not feel like you
मतलब मतलब आपको मन ही नहीं करेगा कि आप
Do worship. There comes a time when you feel
पूजा करें। एक समय ऐसा आता है कि आप फील
may the gods be with us
कर सकते हैं कि देवता हमारे साथ चल रहे
Are. Ok? So at that time, the mantra is
हैं। ठीक है? तो उस समय मंत्र जो है ना
Mantra is a vibration. So your power
मंत्र तो वाइब्रेशन है। तो आपकी शक्ति
When it is fuller than your body proportion
आपके शरीर के अनुपात से जब भर जाती है
With the mantras you will feel that we are no longer worshipping
मंत्रों से तो आपको लगेगा अब हम पूजा नहीं
Do it. Now let us stop chanting for a few days.
करें। अभी हम कुछ दिन जाप छोड़ देते हैं।
When Swami Vivekananda was 34 years old
स्वामी विवेकानंद जब 34 साल के थे ना तो
He told his brother that I
उन्होंने अपने भाई को बता दिया था कि मैं
I will die in six years. They
छ साल में मेरी मृत्यु हो जाएगी। उन्होंने
Asked why will you die? so said
पूछा क्यों आपकी मृत्यु हो जाएगी? तो बोला
that our body does not accommodate this consciousness
कि हमारा जो शरीर है ना वो इस चेतना को
I won't be able to handle it. so a very explosive
नहीं संभाल पाएगा। तो एक बहुत विस्फोटक
The situation will arise and this is what happened Vivekananda
स्थिति हो जाएगी और हुआ भी ऐसा विवेकानंद
He had many diseases. So this
को बहुत सारी बीमारियां हो गई थी। तो यह
It is true that if you always practice meditation and yoga
सही है कि अगर आपको हमेशा ध्यान योग करने
I don't have the desire to, I don't have the desire to chant
की इच्छा ना हो, जाप करने की इच्छा नहीं
Is. so this is perfectly normal what does it mean
है। तो इस परफेक्टली नॉर्मल इसका मतलब
Your body is realizing how much it needs
आपका शरीर यह समझ रहा है कि उसको कितना
How much worship to do, how much meditation to do,
कितना पूजा करना है, कितना ध्यान करना है,
How much to chant? sometimes something something
कितना जाप करना है। कभी-कभी कुछ कुछ
After chanting the mantras, a little
मंत्रों का उच्चारण करने के बाद थोड़ा सा
I start having a headache. and that would be a sign
सर दर्द होने लगता है। और वो एक साइन होती
That's ok stop at least for me. hardly
है कि ओके स्टॉप एटलीस्ट फॉर मी। शायद ही
I have my own system.
मेरा खुद का सिस्टम है।
The chakras must be balanced. If your sir
चक्रों को बैलेंस करना चाहिए। अगर आपके सर
I am in pain that means the mantra
में दर्द हो रहा है उसका मतलब है कि मंत्र
Yours is working. but your crown
आपके काम कर रहे हैं। लेकिन योर क्राउन
The chakra needs a clearing. So by learning it
चक्र नीड्स अ क्लियरिंग। तो उसको सीख करके
And the chakras should be cleared. But
और चक्रों को क्लियर करना चाहिए। पर
How has it become unclean?
अनक्लियर कैसे हुआ है?
I mean how did Cloudy happen? Then he chanted
मतलब क्लाउडडी कैसे हुआ था? फिर वो जाप से
It happens, right? that's what I said, if you
होता है ना। वही मैंने बोला ना कि अगर आप
He keeps on chanting and accumulates energy
जाप करते रहते हैं वह एनर्जी एक्यूमुलेट
It keeps happening. so either you use that energy
होते रहती है। तो आइदर यू यूज़ दैट एनर्जी
you help someone you do something for someone puja
यू हेल्प समबडी आप कुछ किसी के लिए पूजा
do something or pray for someone
कर दो या किसी के लिए कुछ प्रार्थना कर दो
So that energy will be used. Its just you
तो वो एनर्जी यूज़ हो जाएगी। वो सिर्फ आप
If you keep accumulating then it will show it
एक्यूमुलेट करते रहेंगे तो इट विल शो इट्स
Effect. My mentality is that right now
इफेक्ट। मेरी मेंटालिटी यह है कि अभी
Whatever sadhna you have done, the power of that sadhna
जितनी भी साधना करी है उस साधना के पावर
I am starting some new things regarding
को लेकर मैं कुछ-कुछ नई चीजों की शुरुआत
Now I am doing Beyond The on YouTube
कर रहा हूं अब YouTube पर बिय्ड द
podcast. Because I have learned a lot
पॉडकास्ट। क्योंकि बहुत कुछ सीखा भी है
In five to six years. There is a lot to do. We
पांच छ सालों में। बहुत कुछ करना है। हम
We are obviously the world's largest economy for India
हम भारत के लिए ऑब्वियसली पर दुनिया के
For this we also
लिए भी हम
so this outputting creative work this is right
तो ये आउटपुटिंग क्रिएटिव वर्क यह सही
There is a path of sadhana. You get whatever you want now
मार्ग होता है साधना का। आपको अब जो भी आप
He is planning to leave it to his god
प्लान कर रहे हैं वो अपने देवता पे छोड़
Give it. You don't need mantra and sadhna for
दीजिए। यू डोंट नीड मंत्र एंड साधना फॉर
Yourself. Whatever practice you are doing
योरसेल्फ। आप जो भी साधना कर रहे हैं उसका
There will be two fruits. One is that you have this knowledge
दो फल होगा। एक ये कि आपको जो ये ज्ञान है
No, what I said is the cycle of 10 Mahavidyas
ना जो मैंने बोला 10 महाविद्या का जो चक्र
if you keep moving forward in that then that is
है उसमें आप आगे बढ़ते जाएंगे तो दैट इज
Very spiritual. To you in material life
वेरी स्पिरिचुअल। आपको मटेरियल लाइफ में
What you need and what you can do
क्या चाहिए और आप क्या-क्या कर सकते हैं
Leave that to god. Understand one thing. We
वो देवता पे छोड़ दीजिए। एक चीज समझिए। हम
you can see your life only to the extent that
अपने जीवन को वहीं तक देख सकते हैं जहां
We have seen it till now. Are you understanding? mine which
तक हमने देखा है। समझ रहे हैं? मेरा जो
There is exposure, I don't want to end my life there
एक्सपोज़र है ना मैं अपने जीवन को वहीं तक
I can see it. but god bless our life
देख सकता हूं। लेकिन देवता हमारे जीवन को
I watch too much. So if we practice
बहुत ज्यादा देखते हैं। तो अगर हम साधना
and asking the gods to
कर रहे हैं और देवताओं से मांग रहे हैं कि
we may have an X but we mean our
हमारे पास एक्स हो लेकिन हमारा मतलब हमारा
100X is written in my destiny
जो किस्मत है उसमें 100 एक्स लिखा हुआ है
So we stop at X. that's why
तो हम लोग रुक जाते हैं एक्स पे। इसीलिए
Never ever do your sadhana rely on material things
कभी भी साधना जो है ना वो मटेरियल चीजों
You should not do it for this. don't even think
के लिए करनी ही नहीं चाहिए। सोचना भी नहीं
Needed If you are doing a thing then you assume that
चाहिए। आप एक चीज कर रहे हैं तो आप यह मान
Seems like the god wanted you to
लीजिए कि वो देवता ने ऐसा चाहा कि आप
do. If you are successful in that, that is also theirs
करेंगे। उसमें आप सफल हो वो भी उन्हीं का
There is work. That's not your job either. Here
काम है। वह भी आपका काम नहीं है। यहां
If failure was to happen then it wouldn't happen to you
असफल असफल होना होता तो वह नहीं आपको
Would bring it. A seeker should not be afraid of any such thing
लाते। एक साधक को ऐसी किसी चीज में देवता
Do not put any such thing which will fail. Antillean End
नहीं डालते हैं जो कि असफल हो। अंटिल एंड
unleash it is a learning
अनलेस इट इज अ लर्निंग
Again. You just said one thing that
अगेन। आपने एक चीज कही थी अभी कि अ एक
After the point, Devi also came into your life
पॉइंट के बाद देवी भी आ गई आपकी जिंदगी
In. After we worship Bhairava. We this
में। हम भैरव की पूजा करने के बाद। हम इस
I told you about the timeline because I
टाइमलाइन के बारे में बताई बिकॉज़ मेरे
I guess we didn't talk about it last time
ख्याल से पिछली बार हमने इसकी बात नहीं
I had curry it. Hmm. am i also feel that devi
करी थी। हम्म। अम आई आल्सो फील कि देवी
Pooja is less common in Mumbai. we we now
पूजा ना मुंबई में कम होती है। हम हम अब
There is a lot of devotion among the people here. hmm
यहां भक्ति बहुत ज्यादा है लोगों में। हम्
People are very career oriented in this city.
लोग बहुत करियर ओरिएंटेड है इस शहर में।
Mata ki chowki on us, goddess worship, goddess
हम हम पर माता की चौकी, देवी पूजा, देवी
These temples are rarely seen in Bombay.
मंदिर ये कम दिखाई देते हैं बॉम्बे में।
When we go to North then we go to U C
हम हम जब हम नॉर्थ में जा तो तब यू सी
It's more. More prevalent in the South
इट्स मोर। साउथ में भी ज्यादा प्रिवेलेंट
Is. It is also prevalent in the East. because of that
है। ईस्ट में भी प्रिवेलेंट है। उस वजह से
I have seen Devi only in the last 3-4 years
मैंने देवी को सिर्फ पिछले तीन-4 सालों
I have to go in. no up til then it's been
में जाना है। नो अप टिल देन इट्स बीन
Ganpati Krishna Lord Shiva Hum Hum Bat Ye
गणपति कृष्ण भगवान शिवजी हम हम बट ये
It's not just my problem. I feel that
सिर्फ मेरी प्रॉब्लम नहीं है। आई फील कि
This is the problem of my entire generation. Plus
मेरी पूरी जनरेशन की प्रॉब्लम है। प्लस
even online i noticed that definitely
इवन ऑनलाइन मैंने नोटिस किया कि डेफिनेटली
There is a lot of content on Bhairava ji. Shiva
भैरव जी पर बहुत ज्यादा कंटेंट है। शिव जी
But there is too much content. Now on Bhairav ​​ji
पर बहुत ज्यादा कंटेंट है। अब भैरव जी पे
Content Now After 2019 What We Can
कंटेंट अब 2019 के बाद जो है वी कैन
Find. But initially Bhairava was a god.
फाइंड। लेकिन पहले तो भैरव वाज़ अ देवता।
I mean like when we started worshipping Bhairava
मतलब जैसे हमने जब भैरव की पूजा शुरू की
When we were kids, people looked at us as outcasts.
थी तो लोग हमें बड़ा आउटकास्ट देखते थे।
Look, let me tell you a little about this
देखिए मैं बताता हूं थोड़ा सा हम लोग इस
Keep the topic. Bhairava in our life
विषय को रखते हैं। भैरव हमारे जीवन में
Had not come earlier. first in our lives
पहले नहीं आए थे। पहले हमारे जीवन में
Bhagwati had come. We guys, you, yes, okay. Since childhood
भगवती आई थी। हम लोग आप हां ओके। बचपन से
what happened was that we, we, in our home,
क्या था कि हम हम लोग हमारे घर में हमारे
Nana ji was the one who recited Durga Saptashati
नाना जी जो थे ना वो दुर्गा सप्तशती का
Used to recite. And our job was to assist them
पाठ करते थे। और हमारा काम था उनको असिस्ट
to do. So like now Durga Saptashati is going on
करना। तो जैसे अब दुर्गा सप्तशती चल रहा
If so, burn incense there; the lamp is burning
है तो वहां पर धूप जलाना, दीपक जल रहा है
keep watching, do all this and keep doing that
देखता रहना यह सब करना और वैसे करते-करते
The Durga Saptashati which he used to recite I also
जो दुर्गा सप्तशती वह पढ़ते थे वह मुझे भी
I kept remembering and along with it, I was with Bhagwati
याद होता चला गया और साथ में भगवती के साथ
One
एक
I felt very connected. Correct
बहुत एक जुड़ाव हुआ मुझे। ठीक
Is? When we came into the path of Tantra, the first
है? जब हम तंत्र मार्ग में आए तो पहली
The initiation that we had was also Tara Mantra
दीक्षा जो हमारी हुई थी वह भी तारा मंत्र
It started from. So we asked Guruji that
से हुई थी। तो हमने पूछा गुरु जी से कि
Why are we starting with Tara Mantra?
तारा मंत्र से हम क्यों शुरू कर रहे हैं?
So Bhagwati Tara is the motherly form.
तो भगवती तारा जो है वह मातृ स्वरूपा है।
When Mahadev drank poison in the form of a mother
मां के रूप में जब महादेव ने विष पिया ना
During the churning of the ocean he swallowed the poison
समुद्र मंथन में तो विष को उन्होंने कंठ
I restrained myself and saved them from that havoc.
में अपना रोक लिया और उस हलाहल से उनको
I was in a lot of pain. very jealous
बहुत पीड़ा हो रही थी। बहुत जलन हो रही
Was. Then Mahamaya took the form of Bhagwati Tara at that time.
थी। तो महामाया उस समय भगवती तारा के रूप
I came and Mahadev became a small child
में आई और महादेव जो है छोटे बच्चे बन गए
And breastfed them. then from that milk
और उनको स्तनपान कराया। तो उस दूध से
That jealousy of Mahadev stopped. So
महादेव का जो वह जलन था वो रुक गया। तो
In the Tantra path it is said that Bhagwati
तंत्र मार्ग में ऐसा बोलते हैं कि भगवती
If you do sadhna of Tara then
तारा का अगर आप साधना करते हैं ना तो
Mahadev comes running after him. Ok?
महादेव पीछे दौड़े चले आते हैं। ठीक है?
So our beginning was with Bhagwati Durga
तो शुरुआत हमारा हुआ भगवती दुर्गा के
By sadhana. Ok? worship whatever it is
साधना से। ठीक है? पूजा जो भी है जो
It happened as per Durga Shapati. then tara and
दुर्गा शपति के अनुसार हुआ। फिर तारा और
We had a connection with Tarapitha. all this when
तारापीठ से एक हमारा जुड़ाव हुआ। यह सब जब
were doing it so we told you that one time
कर रहे थे तो हमने आपको बताया कि एक समय
It came to pass that there was a great deal of money in our lives
ऐसा आया कि हमारे जीवन में धन का बड़ा
There was a shortage. At that time we should do Tara Sadhna only.
अभाव हो गया। उस समय हम तारा साधना ही कर
Were living. So besides the Guru Mantra we have 10
रहे थे। तो गुरु मंत्र के अलावा हम 10
Mahavid was doing sadhna of Tara and
महाविद तारा की का साधना कर रहे थे और
Only Tara was visible to us. Ok? That
सिर्फ तारा ही हमें दिखती थी। ठीक है? उस
At that time we had also given up Durga Sadhna.
समय हमने दुर्गा साधना भी छोड़ दिया था।
What was your age then? We have started Tara Sadhana
आपकी ऐज क्या थी तब? तारा साधना हमने शुरू
It was done in 2013 and we were born in 84
किया है 2013 में और हमारा जन्म है 84
In.
में।
29 This was it.
29 ये था।
So in 2017 we had a Nathji in Rajasthan
तो 2017 में हमें राजस्थान में एक नाथ जी
meet. Nathji means one who belongs to Nath sect
मिले। नाथ जी का मतलब जो नाथ संप्रदाय से
coming. But what is there is not
आते हैं। लेकिन वहां पे जो है ना वो
The magician is Nath ji. which is very
जादूगर वाले नाथ जी होते हैं। जो बहुत वो
People are Pandora. The meaning of Pandora
लोग भानुमती होता है। भानुमती का अर्थ है
That they show you the tricks. people in it
कि वो आपको ट्रिक्स दिखाते हैं। लोग उसमें
They get stuck. What kind of tricks? So in the room
फंस जाते हैं। कैसा ट्रिक्स? तो रूम में
Shower me with notes. Ok? extract money from the ground
नोट बरसा देना। ठीक है? जमीन से धन निकाल
Give. So that was the way he used to work. Now
देना। तो उस तरीके का वह काम करते थे। अब
That Shivalok of Manohar is no more. So he
नहीं रहे वह शिवलोक मनोहर का। तो उन्होंने
Once I met him, he told me
एक बार मुझ वह मिले तो उन्होंने मुझे बोला
that whatever you are doing right now you need Bhairava
कि आप जो भी कर रहे हैं अभी आपको भैरव
You should do sadhana otherwise you will lose your things
साधना करना चाहिए नहीं तो आपका आपकी चीजें
It won't be ok. I said why ok
ठीक नहीं होंगी। मैंने बोला क्यों ठीक
Won't it be? So he said that it is Maya's work
नहीं होंगी? तो बोला कि माया का काम है
To throw the seekers away. and who balances it
साधकों को पटकना। और उसको बैलेंस कौन करता
Is? Mahadev Shiv form balances it
है? उसको बैलेंस करता है महादेव शिव रूप
In. Then he told me to do Bhairava Sadhna,
में। तो फिर उन्होंने मुझे भैरव साधना,
All these things are the method of Bhairav ​​Sadhana
भैरव साधना की पद्धति यह सारी चीजें
Taught me. After that what happened was that the people there
सिखाई। उसके बाद क्या था कि वहां के जो
Nath is there, he does sadhna on voice
नाथ होते हैं ना वो स्वर पर साधना करते
Are. Meaning he doesn't say any words. they have
हैं। मतलब शब्द नहीं बोलते हैं वो। दे हैव
Some sounds. He doesn't even teach everyone.
सम साउंड्स। वो सबको सिखाते भी नहीं है।
Ok? and the method that he described
ठीक है? और उन्होंने जो पद्धति बताई थी उस
But I have been doing sadhana for two-three years,
पे मैंने दो-तीन साल जो है साधना करा जो
I did what was taught in Bali Pooja.
बलि पूजा सिखाए वो किया।
There was a desire to move beyond that. So
उससे आगे एक बढ़ने की चाहत थी। तो
There was a sadhak who was a big name in Tarapith Kamakhya
एक साधक थे तारापीठ कामाख्या में बड़ा नाम
was his Veernath
था उनका वीरनाथ
Yes, if in modern India there is a very big
जी अगर मॉडर्न इंडिया में कोई बहुत बड़े
When the name of Aghori is taken then he is a doctor
अघोरी का नाम लिया जाता है तो वो डॉक्टर
Ramnath is an Aghori. And those who direct
रामनाथ अघोरी हैं। और उनके जो डायरेक्ट
The disciple was Veernath ji. So Veernath ji
डिसाइपल थे वो वीरनाथ जी थे। तो वीरनाथ जी
When I met him, I started crying.
से जब मैं मिला था तो मैं मतलब रोने लगा।
I had heard his name so much. He is in Ranchi
इतना उनका नाम सुना था। वो रांची में उनका
There is an ashram. yes it is. He is now deceased.
आश्रम है। है है। वह अब दिवंगत हो गए।
Shiva went to heaven in 125 years. So when
शिवलोक गमन हो गया 125 साल में। तो जब
When we went to meet him, we went thinking that
उनसे हम मिलने गए ना तो हम यह सोच कर गए
We were thinking that we will take the mantra of Bhairava from him. Correct
थे कि इनसे हम भैरव का मंत्र लेंगे। ठीक
Is? So we went to meet him. He was very happy
है? तो हम गए उनसे मिलने। वो बड़े खुश हुए
We sat together for five to six hours. Very
मिलकर के और हम पांच छ घंटे बैठे। बहुत
All kinds of things happened. Food happened, whatever happened
तरह की बातें हुई। भोजन हुआ जो हुआ सब
Happened. But we couldn't tell them that we
हुआ। लेकिन हम उनको बोल नहीं पाए कि हमें
Please give me the Bhairav ​​mantra. Ok. say that mean
आप भैरव मंत्र दे दो। ठीक है। वो मतलब बोल
I couldn't even find it. There was no chance, no meaning
ही नहीं पाए। ना मौका लगा ना मतलब
It felt appropriate to talk to him. a few days
एप्रोप्रियट लगा कि उनसे बोल पाए। कुछ दिन
Went again later. Then we sat for 5-6 hours
बाद फिर गए। फिर 5 6 घंटे हम लोग बैठे फिर
Couldn't speak. Well, your 5 and a quarter year old saint
नहीं बोल पाए। अच्छा सवा5 साल का संत आपके
if someone is sitting in front of you then you should wait 10 minutes before speaking.
सामने बैठा है तो आपको बोलने से पहले 10
I have to think many times whether I should say it or not
बार सोचना पड़ता है कि हम बोले कि नहीं
Speak.
बोले।
Went again on the third day. On the third day we thought
तीसरे दिन फिर गए। तीसरे दिन हमने सोचा कि
I will speak today and then I will not be able to speak.
आज बोल ही देंगे और फिर नहीं बोल पाए हम।
Meaning, I could not speak even though I wanted to. And we started to go
मतलब चाह के नहीं बोल पाए। और हम जाने लगे
That okay Guru Maharaj, we are leaving. when we
कि ठीक है गुरु महाराज हम चलते हैं। जब हम
As he came out of the gate he entered a small room
गेट से निकलने लगे एक छोटा सा रूम में वह
I used to sleep in a corner, so he said
एक कोने में सोए रहते थे तो उन्होंने बोला
that you will be able to handle Bhairav ​​if you ask a direct question
कि तुम भैरव को संभाल लोगे सीधा सवाल तो
We said yes, we will handle this much
हमने बोला हां हम संभाल लेंगे तो इतना
It is not easy to handle Bhairav, we are not
आसान नहीं है भैरव को संभालना नहीं हम
Gurudev will take care of it and after that very
संभाल लेंगे गुरुदेव और उसके बाद बहुत ही
Bhairav ​​temple in Ranchi miraculously
चमत्कारी ढंग से भैरव मंदिर रांची में
After the Bhairav ​​temple was built, Bhagwati's temple was built
बना भैरव मंदिर बनने के बाद भगवती की
The establishment of Bhagwati which was established
स्थापना हुई भगवती की स्थापना जो हुई वो
We have a place called Ramnagar in Bihar. There
को हमने बिहार में एक जगह है रामनगर। वहां
By inviting Bhagawati from your own
से भगवती को आमंत्रित करके अपने अपने
is placed in place. and then there again
स्थान पर रखा है। और उसके बाद वहां पर फिर
Durga Puja has begun. So the only one like that
दुर्गा पूजा शुरू हुआ। तो एकमात्र ऐसा
It is Durga Puja which lasts for nine days
दुर्गा पूजा है जहां पे नौ दिन पूरा जो है
Durga is worshipped according to Tantra method. Now
तंत्र विधि से दुर्गा की पूजा होती है। अब
So Durga Puja too is going to become extinct
तो दुर्गा पूजा भी जो है वह विलुप्त होने
Put. You are talking about here. I
लगा। आप यहां की बातें कर रहे हैं। मैं
I was watching Durga Puja here. So
यहां का दुर्गा पूजा देख रहा था। तो
It is said in the scriptures that whatever you have is different
शास्त्रोक्त है कि आपको जो है ना अलग-अलग
We bring soil from this place and make Durga from it
जगह का जो है मिट्टी ला के उससे ही दुर्गा
The vigraha of Ka is created
का का जो विग्रह है उसका निर्माण होता है
The puja which goes on for nine days, I have seen it at many places
जो नौ दिन पूजा चलता है तो बहुत जगह मैंने
It was seen here that those POP statues were moving
यहां देखा कि वह पीओपी की मूर्तियां चल
It is like a thing in which life cannot come.
रही हैं जिसमें प्राण ही नहीं आ सकती है।
At our place too, the Kalash would be placed from the fourth day
हमारे यहां भी चौथे दिन से कलश बैठा देते
Are. What is fundamentally religion now?
हैं। मूलभूत रूप से क्या है ना कि अब धर्म
is coming back. I can say this. So
वापस आ रहा है। यह मैं बोल सकता हूं। तो
But in the last 20 years the entire religion has
लेकिन पिछले 20 सालों में धर्म का पूरा
Was destroyed. In the last 20 years, 202
नाश किया गया। पिछले 20 सालों में 202
in years yes since 2000 since 2000 approximately why
सालों में हां 2000 से 2000 से लगभग क्यों
Our generation or those just before us
हमारा जनरेशन या हमसे जो जस्ट पहले वाले
When that generation grew up, they were separated from religion
जनरेशन जब वो बड़े हुए ना तो उनको धर्म से
There was not much attachment. We mostly live in India
बहुत लगाव नहीं था। हम मोस्टली जो इंडिया
Wasn't it a place for displaced people?
था ना वो डिस्प्लेस्ड लोगों का एक जगह बन
Everyone left their village and came somewhere to earn money
गया कि सब अपना गांव छोड़ के कहीं कमाने आ
have been. So those who are coming to earn, their first
रहे हैं। तो जो कमाने आ रहे हैं उनका पहला
The aim was that their child should also study
उद्देश्य यह रहता था कि उनका बच्चा भी पढ़
Whatever I have, I started earning. Ok? So the one who is
के जो है कमाने लगे। ठीक है? तो वह जो एक
Religion requires mental stability
मेंटल स्टेबिलिटी चाहिए होती है धर्म को
He is the Maximum India's to follow
फॉलो करने के लिए वो मैक्सिमम इंडिया का
It was not there. Well, on the side where this stability was
नहीं था। अच्छा जिस तरफ ये स्टेबिलिटी थी
Where the displacement is less
जहां पर डिस्प्लेसमेंट जो है वो कम है
There, religion is going on as it is.
वहां जो है धर्म एज इट इज चल रहा है।
But in North India and wherever you see
लेकिन नॉर्थ इंडिया और जहां पर आप देखिएगा
that modernization is where factories are built
कि मॉडर्नाइजेशन है जहां पे फैक्ट्रीज बने
The religion there was completely destroyed.
वहां पर धर्म जो है पूरा ही नाश हो गया।
Now the AP center of Durga Puja is Kolkata
अब दुर्गा पूजा का एपी सेंटर तो कोलकाता
Is. So many days for the communists in Kolkata
है। कोलकाता में कम्युनिस्टों का इतना दिन
It remained a secret. the government system that is still in place
राज रहा। अभी भी वहां जो शासन तंत्र है वह
It is very secular. So that is also the goddess's
बहुत सेुलर है। तो वह भगवती का भी को भी
They make it secular. without weapons
सेुलर बना देते हैं। बिना अस्त्र-शस्त्रों
is worshipped. Isn't it? So this is going on.
के पूजा होती है। है ना? तो यह चल रहा है।
So when Durga was worshipped in our place
तो हमारे यहां जब पूजा होती थी दुर्गा की
So when we used to see it, we felt
तो हम देखते थे जब हम तो हमें लगता था
No, there should be such worship at a place where
नहीं एक जगह तो ऐसी पूजा होनी चाहिए जहां
But the whole method is as per the rules and regulations
पे पूरा ही जो विधि है विधान है उसी तरीके
Should be worshipped? So for the past six years now
से पूजा हो। तो वह अभी पिछले छ सालों से
Now Durga is being worshipped in our temple
अब हमारे मंदिर पर दुर्गा की पूजा हो रही
Is. Right or wrong way to worship
है। पर पूजा करने का सही या गलत तरीका
Where is it written? The first topic we
कहां लिखा गया है? हम सबसे पहला विषय यह
That puja is done in two ways. Agamas and
है कि पूजा दो तरीके से होता है। आगम और
Corporation. This is one way, which is Tantra path. So
निगम। एक तो यह है जो तंत्र मार्ग है। तो
In the path of Tantra, the book of Tantra path
तंत्र मार्ग में जो तंत्र मार्ग के पुस्तक
are you to him
हैं उसको आप
Study under some guru and
पढ़िए किसी गुरु के अंडर में और उसको
Understand it and then do it. that tantra path
समझिए और फिर उसको करिए। वह तंत्र मार्ग
Worship is done with it. The second Vedic law
से पूजा होता है। जो दूसरा जो वैदिक विधान
There is a scriptural rule for worship, right?
है पूजा का है ना जो शास्त्रीय विधान है
We and you don't have to do that puja.
पूजा का वह हमें और आपको करना ही नहीं है।
His simple principle is that you
उसका सीधा सिद्धांत है कि आप किसी पंडित
Call him. You can only be a host to it
को बुलाइए। आप सिर्फ उसमें यजमान हो सकते
Are. You cannot perform the puja on your own. So
हैं। खुद से पूजा आप कर ही नहीं सकते। तो
don't put your mind to it at all
उसमें बिल्कुल ही दिमाग ही नहीं लगाना
That is how puja should be done. means you
चाहिए कि पूजा कैसे करना चाहिए। मतलब आप
You are saying that puja is mostly done in everyone's house
कह रहे हो जो पूजा मोस्टली हर किसी के घर
It happens to us which our mother always does
पे होती है जो हमारी मम्मी करती है हमेशा
We will actually do that by bringing a Pandit.
हम वो एक्चुअली एक पंडित को लाकर करना
We don't need those who worship at home
चाहिए नहीं हम लोग जो घर में पूजा करते
Yes, that is tantric worship, okay, that is Vedic
हैं वो तांत्रिक पूजा है ठीक है वो वैदिक
It is not everyone's matter who is in everyone's house
नहीं हर किसी की बात हर किसी के घर में जो
People also worship lord Krishna
लोग अह कृष्ण भगवान की पूजा भी करते हैं
Absolutely respectful of duty
बिल्कुल रेस्पेक्टिव ऑफ ड्यूटी बिल्कुल
Because as soon as you come to Panch Puja
क्योंकि आप जैसे ही पंच पूजा में आ जाते
If yes then it is a Tantric puja. What
हैं तो वो तांत्रिक पूजा होती है। क्या
Is Panch Puja performed? Panch puja means you
होती है पंच पूजा? पंच पूजा मतलब आपने
You lit the incense stick in front of the deity
दिया जलाया देवता के सामने आपने अगरबत्ती
You lit the fire, you offered it to them
जलाया आपने उनको नैवेद्य दिया आपने उनको
You offered sandalwood to him and offered flowers to him
चंदन चढ़ाया आपने उसको उनको पुष्प चढ़ाया
You offered these five things to this Tantrik
ये पांच चीज आपने चढ़ा दिया यह तांत्रिक
The method is in the Vedic method of worship that
पद्धति है पूजा की वैदिक पद्धति में है कि
You will light the havan and perform it, is that okay?
आप हवन जलाइएगा और हवन करिएगा ठीक है ना
Just this, as soon as you performed the Panch Puja
सिर्फ इतना ही तो जैसे ही आपने पंच पूजा
does it mean that you are a tantrik
किया उसका अर्थ होता है कि आप तांत्रिक
Worshiping as per the method. Ok. Are you
पद्धति से पूजा कर रहे हैं। ओके। आर यू
saying that most of the people especially this
सेइंग कि मोस्टली जितने भी लोग स्पेशली यह
We are still listening to that podcast
वाला पडकास्ट अब तक सुन रहे हैं हम उन सों
have I ever worshipped in my life
ने कभी अपनी जिंदगी में पूजा करी है हम तो
He has already used the system.
ऑलरेडी तंत्र का उपयोग करा है उन्होंने।
they're doing it, they're doing it. you kept the defiance
कर रहे हैं वो कर रहे हैं। आपने विग्रह रख
If you take it then the idol is a device. Hmm. You
लिया तो विग्रह एक यंत्र है। हम्। आप
Keeping the yantra and chanting mantras along with it
यंत्र रख रहे हैं और साथ में मंत्रों का
If you are pronouncing it then you are doing tantra
उच्चारण कर रहे हैं तो आप तंत्र कर रहे
Are. And now in the coming years we will be
हैं। और अब आने वाले सालों में हम ये एक
The high level will be in an advanced version
हाई लेवल एक एडवांस्ड वर्जन में होगा
In our country. Yes. This is a fight.
हमारे देश में। हां। ये झगड़ा है।
Absolutely. So home
बिल्कुल। तो घर
You can advance while sitting
बैठे-बैठे अ आपकी एडवांसमेंट हो सकती है
On the path of Tantra. This is what we are saying to you. Yes.
तंत्र मार्ग पे। हम यही कह रहे हो आप। जी।
Ok. But you talked about Durga Puja
ओके। पर जो आपने दुर्गा पूजा की बात करी
you said i think what i understood
आपने कहा कि आई थिंक व्हाट आई अंडरस्टुड
When you worship Shakti, that is worship
इज जब आप शक्ति की पूजा करते हो अ वो पूजा
It is a little fiery, a little aggressive
ही थोड़ी फायरी होती है थोड़ी उग्र होती
And such fierce worships were probably not there 100 years ago
है और ऐसी उग्र पूजाएं शायद 100 साल पहले
200 years ago we were very normal in India
200 साल पहले बहुत नॉर्मल थी भारत में हम
But now she has become normal a lot because
पर अब वो नॉर्मल सी चली गई है अ लॉट बिकॉज़
of British Rule etc. in which case
ऑफ़ ब्रिटिश रूल वगैरह जिस स्थिति में
Our country had different factors. but that
हमारा देश था अलग-अलग फैक्टर्स थे। बट वो
Everything will come back now. We just now worship that fiery
सब अब लौट कर आएगा। हम अभी उस उग्र पूजा
Let's talk a little bit about it. we came
के बारे में थोड़ा सा बात करते हैं। हम आई
No, now we will know a little about the practice of sacrifice.
नो कि अब हम बलि प्रथा के बारे में थोड़ा
I will talk to you. Let’s start from there
सा बात करेंगे। वहां से शुरुआत करते हैं
Because this is an internet friendly topic.
क्योंकि ये एक इंटरनेट फ्रेंडली टॉपिक है।
Look at this Tantra Shastra. Ok? on that
देखिए जो तंत्रशास्त्र है। ठीक है? उस पे
There is no point in debating. You
डिबेट करने से कोई मतलब ही नहीं है। आप
You will see that those who oppose the practice of sacrifice
देखेंगे कि जो लोग बलि प्रथा का विरोध कर
Those people are calling themselves Vaishnavs
रहे हैं वो लोग अपने आप को वैष्णव बोलते
Are. Ok? And since he is a Vaishnav
हैं। ठीक है? और क्योंकि वह वैष्णव हैं तो
They feel that you should not make sacrifices. Ok?
उनको लगता है कि आप बलि नहीं दें। ठीक है?
Because he is a vegetarian. Mr Karpatri
क्योंकि वह वेजिटेरियन है। करपात्री जी
Maharaj it is okay that at the last moment of the religious assembly
महाराज ठीक है जो धर्म सभा के अंतिम
Was the president. He spoke on the subject
अध्यक्ष रहे। उन्होंने इस विषय पर बताया
It was when one of his devotees came and
था कि जब उनके उनके एक भक्त आए थे और
He had asked that Agnihotra Brahmin
उन्होंने पूछा था वो अग्निहोत्र ब्राह्मण
Were. Agnihotra havan is performed to the Sun
थे। अग्निहोत्र का हवन होता है सूर्य के
For. So we asked him to perform a wet havan
लिए। तो उनसे पूछा था कि हम गीला हवन करें
Or perform dry havan. this story is complete
या सूखा हवन करें। यह कहानी पूरी
Shankaracharya Mahabhag has also told this. Meaning
शंकराचार्य महाभाग ने भी बताया है। मतलब
Wet havan means that first the sacrifice
गीला हवन का मतलब होता है कि पहले बलि
And with that meat again for the sun
देते हैं और उस मांस से फिर सूर्य के लिए
We perform havan for the Sun. Ok? And
हवन करते हैं सूर्य के लिए। ठीक है? और
Dry havan means the havan which is performed with the havan material
सूखा हवन का मतलब जो हवन सामग्री से हवन
It happens. Ok? So he said that
होता है। ठीक है? तो उन्होंने बोला था कि
You should perform wet havan. means first sunrayan
गीला हवन करिए आप। मतलब पहले सूर्यारायण
Sacrifice it and then offer it to him as havan
को बलि दीजिए और फिर उससे जो है आपको हवन
Should be done. What is sacrificed?
करना चाहिए। किस चीज की बलि दी जाती है?
Of the goat. Isn't it? Those of us who follow the path of Tantra
बकरे की। है ना? जो तंत्र मार्ग के हम लोग
If there are people then the Panchamakar prevails amongst us.
लोग हैं तो हम लोगों में पंचमकार चलता है।
Without meat, our worship is not complete
बिना मांस के जो है हमारा पूजा नहीं होता
Is. Is it okay? So we debate in Tantra
है। ठीक है ना? तो तंत्र में तो हम डिबेट
I won't do it at all. if anybody is even talking
ही नहीं करेंगे। अगर कोई अगर बोल भी रहा
that you should not sacrifice then it does
है कि आपको बलि नहीं देना चाहिए तो इट डज
Doesn't matter. It does not matter to us whether
नॉट मैटर। हमें अंतर ही नहीं पड़ता है कि
Who is saying what? That practice of ours
कौन क्या बोल रहा है। हमारा वो प्रैक्टिस
Is. It means that after someone
है। मतलब ये ऐसा है कि किसी के बाद में
Someone else is expressing his opinion. so someone's
कोई और अपना मंतव्य रख रहा है। तो किसी का
The intent doesn't matter. what is religion
मंतव्य कोई मतलब नहीं रखता है। धर्म क्या
are you speaking? That's all I have to see.
बोल रहा है? बस उतना ही देखना है।
Effectively all sadhna including basic
इफेक्टिवली ऑल साधना इंक्लूडिंग बेसिक
If we sit in one place and do meditation
मेडिटेशन हम अगर कोई एक जगह बैठकर किसी
Chant the mantra HAM ENIDE THE MIND. We
मंत्र का जाप करें हम इनाइड द माइंड। हम
There is an energy build up. Are we okay?
एक एनर्जी बिल्ड अप होती है। हम ठीक है?
Over the years I'm from. So, what is your diet?
ओवर इयर्स आई एम से। तो, क्या आपके डाइट
Because of that energy build up gets affected
की वजह से वह एनर्जी बिल्ड अप अफेक्ट हो
Can it? as it is said that chakra can gate
सकती है? जैसे कहते हैं कि चक्र कैन गेट
Blocked because of non veg etc. So, I
ब्लॉक्ड बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ नॉनवेज वगैरह। तो, मैंने
I have thought a lot about this subject.
इसी विषय के बारे में बहुत कुछ सोचा है।
and please correct me if you say you are you
एंड प्लीज करेक्ट मी इफ यू यू यू यू यू यू
You I'm wrong. butt i think different mantra
यू आई एम रोंग। बट मुझे लगता है अलग मंत्र
has different rules. but is that right
के अलग रूल्स होते हैं। बट क्या यह सही है
or wrong? See, there are no different rules for different mantras
या गलत? देखिए अलग मंत्र के अलग रूल नहीं
There are. Different gods have different rules.
होते हैं। अलग देवता के अलग रूल होते हैं।
So, when you are doing sadhana for someone, right?
मतलब आप जब किसी की साधना कर रहे हैं ना
So gradually your nature and behavior
तो धीरे-धीरे आपका जो नेचर और बिहेवियर है
Nor does he become like your East. That
ना वो आपके ईस्ट के जैसा होते जाता है। कि
If you are a devotee of Narayan. Now Narayan who
अगर आप नारायण के भक्त हैं। अब नारायण जो
You will do whatever you enjoy, right? we are this
भोग करते हैं वही आप करेंगे ना। हम ये उस
It works in this manner. Meaning, you should understand one thing.
तरीके से चलता है। मतलब आप एक चीज समझिए।
the body of a human being or
एक मनुष्य का जो शरीर है ना या मनुष्य का
You have a brain, you can see it in any dimension
दिमाग है ना आप उसको किसी भी डायमेंशन में
Can not push. you can suppress
पुश नहीं कर सकते हैं। आप सप्रेस कर सकते
Are. And the thing which you will suppress
हैं। और जिस चीज को आप सप्रेस करेंगे ना
He is in some form or the other and he is
वो किसी ना किसी फॉर्म में और वो हो के
Will get back to you. Ok? So when you
आपके पास वापस आएगा। ठीक है? तो जब आप
If you are following religion then no religion
धर्म को फॉलो कर रहे हैं ना तो धर्म को ना
should allow it to flow as you
फ्लो करने देना चाहिए कि जैसे-जैसे आप
As you begin to practice,
साधना करना शुरू करेंगे जैसे-जैसे आप
When you follow the gods in the same way
देवताओं को जब फॉलो करेंगे ना जैसे-जैसे
His grace will keep coming to you and things will be in your favor
उनकी कृपा आप तक आती जाएगी तो चीजें आपके
will change automatically in life and that is
जीवन में अपने आप बदलती जाएंगी और वो ऐसा
You might think that I am the one doing this.
होगा कि आपको लगेगा यह मैं ही कर रहा हूं।
Then you may have what God wants
तब जो है आपको हो सकता है कि देवता चाहे
that you become a vegetarian but that god
कि आप शाकाहारी हो जाए लेकिन वह देवता
will take you to a place where you will feel
वहां तक आपको ले जाएंगे कि आपको लगेगा
I don't need it. the day you think
मुझे इसकी जरूरत नहीं है। आप जिस दिन सोच
because if I don't do that then I will be very
लिए कि अच्छा ऐसा नहीं करूंगा तो मैं बहुत
I will develop in sadhana. it does not
डेवलप कर जाऊंगा साधना में। यह नहीं होता
Is. This does not happen. One might understand that
है। ऐसा नहीं होता है। कोई यह समझ ले कि
I have completely understood the game of Mahamaya.
मैं महामाया के खेल को पूरा समझ गया हूं।
So the gods could not understand what we understood
तो देवता नहीं समझ पाए हम क्या समझ
Will find it. you're gonna get all this mixed up
पाएंगे। कि आप इन सब चीजों को उलझा लेंगे
By not eating food. Isn't it? And I last
खाना नहीं खा के। है ना? और मैंने पिछली
Bar also said that food is a matter of option
बार भी बोला था कि फूड इज अ मैटर ऑफ ऑप्शन
For those who have money. We give you the money
फॉर दोस हु हैव मनी। हम आपके पास पैसा
If not, then you do not have a god. As such
नहीं है तो आपके पास देवता नहीं है। ऐसा
It doesn't happen. You can eat anything if you are a god
नहीं होता। आप कुछ भी खाओ आप अगर देवता
If you are engrossed in me then the god is for you
में रमे हुए हो तो देवता जो है आपको
Will meet. Sadhna with Do You Feel That Diet
मिलेंगे। डू यू फील कि डाइट से साधना
It gets affected. See, this doesn't happen to me
अफेक्ट होती है। देखिए मेरे साथ ऐसा नहीं
It happened till today. Ok? There is such a thing as any
हुआ आज तक। ठीक है? कोई भी चीज ऐसी चीज है
not the one to whom you give too much priority
ना जिसको आप बहुत ज्यादा प्रायोरिटी
I will give. Ok? It will affect your sadhana.
देंगे। ठीक है? इट विल अफेक्ट योर साधना।
What Why Should We Just Talk About Food?
व्हाट व्हाई शुड वी जस्ट टॉक अबाउट फूड?
Ok? If you do deep meditation and
ठीक है? अगर आप डीप मेडिटेशन करते हैं और
If your phone is important to you, then it
आपके लिए आपका फोन महत्वपूर्ण है तो वो
Even the phone will distract you from your sadhana. A
फोन भी जो है आपको साधना से भटका देगा। अ
Knock on the Door Can Like Green Your Meditation
नॉक ऑन द डोर कैन लाइक ग्रीन योर मेडिटेशन
And If You Think Your Meditation Is Very
एंड इफ यू थिंक योर मेडिटेशन इज़ वेरी
Importent. Like you did Kriya Yoga
इंपॉर्टेंट। लाइक आप क्रिया योग आपने किया
Is. So this is taught in Kriya Yoga
है। तो क्रिया योग में यह सिखाया जाता है
that even if a mosquito bites you it doesn't
कि इवन इफ अ मॉस्किटो बाइट्स यू इट डज़ नॉट
Affect you. And they never talk about food. Give
अफेक्ट यू। एंड दे नेवर टॉक अबाउट फूड। दे
Talk about Sadhana. Isn't it? so the more you
टॉक अबाउट साधना। है ना? सो द मोर यू
Create a distraction. You for yourself
क्रिएट द डिस्ट्रैक्शन। आप खुद अपने लिए
you set it that if I do this then it will happen
सेट करते हो कि यह अगर मैं करूंगा तो ऐसा
Will not done. If I do this it won't happen
नहीं होगा। यह अगर मैं करूंगा तो ऐसा नहीं
will be. If I do this then this will not happen. Now
होगा। यह अगर करूंगा तो ऐसा नहीं होगा। अब
People say that it is tamasic food,
लोग बोलते हैं कि तामसिक भोजन है, सात्विक
There is food. Ok? then you will eat satvik food
भोजन है। ठीक है? तो सात्विक भोजन करेंगे
Then your mind will remain pure. so what does that mean
तो आपका मन शुद्ध रहेगा। तो मतलब दैट मींस
That means as much crime is happening right now
कि जितने मतलब जितना अभी क्राइम हो रहा है
He is 100% non vegetarian
वो 100% जो है नॉन वेजिटेरियन कर रहे हैं
What? Isn't it? That is why it means tamasic food
क्या? है ना? तभी तो मतलब तामसिक भोजन
by doing more good work
करने से और जितने अच्छे कार्य हो रहे हैं
Are they all vegetarian? As such
वह सारे वेजिटेरियन कर रहे हैं क्या? ऐसा
What is it? Is there any such buffering system in the world?
है क्या? ऐसा कोई बफरकेशन है दुनिया में
Isn't it? So what are you eating?
नहीं है ना? तो आप भोजन क्या कर रहे हैं?
It might change your mind about it
उससे आपका विचार परिवर्तित हो जाए इसका
Meaning your idea is weak. Ok? They
मतलब आपका विचार कमजोर है। ठीक है? वो
Getting affected by anything. Meaning
अफेक्ट हो जा रहा है किसी भी चीज से। मतलब
You are saying that meditation and chanting of mantras
आप कह रहे हो कि साधना और मंत्र उच्चारण
so much
इतने ज्यादा
We are such powerful weapons that actually no one
पावरफुल शस्त्र हैं हम कि एक्चुअली किसी
It is not affected by any thing. No effect
भी चीज से अफेक्ट नहीं होता। इफेक्ट नहीं
It happens. But if your mind is inside your heart
होता है। पर अगर आपके दिमाग दिल के अंदर
I have such doubts, self-doubts, then maybe
ऐसे डाउट है, सेल्फ डाउट है फिर शायद
It might be affected. See in Sanatana Dharma
अफेक्ट हो सकता है। देखिए सनातन धर्म में
By eating these five things you can follow Sanatana Dharma
पांच चीजों को खाने से आप सनातन धर्म धर्म
go out of
के बाहर चले जाते
Are. So let me tell you one more thing now.
हैं। तो मैं अभी एक चीज और बता देता हूं।
99.999% people are outside Sanatan Dharma.
99.999% लोग सनातन धर्म से बाहर हैं।
because what are the things that mean who
क्योंकि व्हाट आर द थिंग्स दैट मतलब कौन
These are the things that you eat
सी ऐसी चीजें हैं जो कि आप खाते हैं तो
They are excluded from Sanatan Dharma. So garlic
सनातन धर्म से बाहर हो जाते हैं। तो लहसुन
Onion fine mushrooms. Ok? Pork and a
प्याज ठीक है मशरूम। ठीक है? पोर्क और एक
I can't remember the item right now. But
आइटम है मुझे अभी ध्यान नहीं आ रहा। बट
Garlic, onions, mushrooms. Mushrooms mean
लहसुन, प्याज, मशरूम। मशरूम तो मतलब
Vegetarians can also eat it. Isn't it? and this
वेजिटेरियंस भी खा लेते हैं। है ना? और यह
There is pork and cow. So all of these things
पोर्क और गाय तो है ही। तो इन सब चीजों को
By eating this you are out of Sanatan Dharma
खाने से आप जो है सनातन धर्म से बाहर हो
Let's go. When we talk about Sanatana Dharma
जाते हैं। जब हम सनातन धर्म की बात करते
Isn't it Sanatan Dharma is not confined to
हैं ना सनातन धर्म इज नॉट कनफाइंड टू
Humans. Sanatana Dharma which is of the Gods
ह्यूमंस। सनातन धर्म जो है ना देवताओं के
It is for animals and also for humans.
लिए भी है और मनुष्यों के लिए भी है।
All knowledge was given to humans in some part
मनुष्यों को कुछ भाग दिया गया सारे ज्ञान
That which he can understand. Let us take the Mahabharata
का जो वह समझ सके। महाभारत का लेते हैं
The epic is our history book. When
महाकाव्य जो इतिहास ग्रंथ है हमारा। जब
Vyasa wrote the Mahabharata, so
व्यास जी ने महाभारत लिखा ना तो उसको
It was finished in 24,000 verses. He
24,000 श्लोकों में खत्म कर दिया था। वह
The one who was there for Rs 24,000 was the main principal.
24,000 जो था ना वह मेन प्रिंसिपल था।
After reading it, anyone can understand Mahabharata.
उसको पढ़ के जो है कोई भी महाभारत समझ
can't do it. then it was added to
नहीं सकता है। फिर उसमें ऐड किया गया
History. So it became a history book and then
इतिहास। तो वो इतिहास ग्रंथ बना और तब वो
The Mahabharata which we read consisted of 1 lakh verses
हुआ 1 लाख श्लोकों का जो महाभारत हम पढ़ते
Are. But this Rs 1 lakh that was given to us
हैं। बट यह जो 1 लाख हम लोगों को दिया गया
Yes, this is a lesson from the Mahabharata. which is complete
है, यह एक पाठ है महाभारत का। जो पूरा
Mahabharata is available for the gods.
महाभारत है वो देवताओं के लिए उपलब्ध है।
It is not meant for humans at all. that's why
वो मनुष्यों के लिए है ही नहीं। इसीलिए
There are a lot of things that we
बहुत सारी ऐसी चीजें आती है जो कि हम
People have been told as a rule.
लोगों को एज अ रूल बता दिया गया है।
Because it is beyond our understanding to understand it
क्योंकि उसको समझ पाना हमारे विवेक के परे
Is. An obvious question is that then that rule
है। एक ऑब्वियस सवाल ये है कि फिर वो रूल
where is the book? Why didn't you give it to me in my childhood?
बुक है कहां? मुझे बचपन में क्यों नहीं दी
Is this rule book gone? because the man that
गई ये रूल बुक? क्योंकि मनुष्य उस चीज को
can not understand. But what about humans
समझ नहीं सकते हैं। लेकिन क्या मनुष्यों
For which she can never be available? yes
के लिए वो कभी उपलब्ध नहीं हो सकती? हो
It can. In our Vedas, there is mention of Yajnas
सकती है। हमारे वेदों में यज्ञों की
The number and method of Yagya has been explained. If
संख्या और यज्ञ की पद्धति बताई गई है। अगर
In a number you can read that Veda and
एक संख्या में आप उस वेद को पढ़ करके और
If he performs the yajna then you will be free from the human
वह यज्ञ कर लेते हैं तो आप मनुष्य से
they become gods. So, humans have to
देवता बन जाते हैं। तो मनुष्यों को अपने
The path to becoming a god in life was given
जीवन में देवता बनने का मार्ग दे दिया गया
Is. So if you follow him and become a god
है। तो आप अगर उसका अनुसरण करके देवता बन
If you go, it is available for you. I am
जाते हैं तो आपके लिए वो उपलब्ध है। आई एम
Thinking about how Sanatan Dharma has progressed for centuries
थिंकिंग कि सदियों से सनातन धर्म आगे कैसे
increased? because we have been here for centuries
बढ़ा? क्योंकि हम लोग सदियों से हैं ही
No. We have been around for many clever ages.
नहीं। हम लोग तो कई चातुर युगों से हैं।
We have been here for many eons. We will never end
कई कल्पों से हम लोग हैं। हम लोग कभी खत्म
It did not happen. We are infinite, aren't we? of Sanatana
ही नहीं हुए। हम लोग अनंत है ना। सनातन का
What does it mean? Which has been going on since the beginning.
मतलब क्या है? जो शुरू से चला आ रहा है।
We understand this in a very normal way
इसको बड़ा बड़े नॉर्मल तरीके से हम समझते
Are. Now there was Gandhi. Ok? Mahatma Gandhi
हैं। अब गांधी थे। ठीक है? महात्मा गांधी
Were. how do you know about them
थे। उनके बारे में आप कैसे जानते
Are? By reading. You haven't seen it. Is
हैं? पढ़ के। आपने देखा तो नहीं है। है
No? even when the end of mankind comes
ना? जब मनुष्यों का अंत होता है ना तब भी
The gods live. Ok? Like we told you
देवता रहते हैं। ठीक है? जैसे हमने आपको
told that when Shri
बताया कि जब श्री
Ram was crying
राम रो रहे थे
When he is wandering in the separation from his wife
अपनी भार्या के वियोग में जब वह घूम रहे
At that time, Mahadev was in the jungle, only Ram Katha
थे ना जंगल में उस समय महादेव राम कथा ही
I was listening. Ok?
सुन रहे थे। ठीक है?
And even earlier people knew the Rama Katha which
और पहले से भी वो राम कथा लोग जानते थे जो
still going. Ok? So that time loop
अभी चल रहा है। ठीक है? तो वो जो टाइम लूप
the concept is not that time is stagnant and
का कांसेप्ट है ना कि टाइम इज स्टैगेंट और
We are changing stations. it
हम लोग जो है वी आर चेंजिंग स्टेशंस। यह
This is told in every story of Sanatan Dharma.
सनातन धर्म के हर कहानी में बताया गया है।
Ok? So our guardians are above us
ठीक है? तो हमारे ऊपर हमारे गार्डियंस
The ones sitting here are gods. time is
बैठे हुए हैं जो देवता हैं। टाइम इज
Stagnant and we are changing stations. Wow
स्टैगेंट एंड वी आर चेंजिंग स्टेशंस। वाह
Meaning what was happening 2000 years ago is happening now
मतलब जो 2000 साल पहले हो रहा था वो अभी
It is also happening somewhere. Cycle of Birth
भी कहीं हो रहा है। साइकिल साइकिल ऑफ़ बर्थ
And the same character. she body yes. may be some
एंड द सेम कैरेक्टर। शी बॉडी यस। मे बी सम
Another soul but the story remains same. you this
अदर आत्मा बट द स्टोरी रिमें सेम। आप ये
Do you believe that you are in the same family?
मानते हो कि एक ही फैमिली में आपका
Rebirth happens. It is possible this would have been
पुनर्जन्म होता है। हो सकता है। ये होता
Is.
है।
People who helped us create our first podcast
जिन लोगों ने हमारा पहला वाला पॉडकास्ट
I haven't seen them, even a little
नहीं देखा है उनके लिए भी थोड़ा सा
It is necessary to provide contact. you know the same horror
कांटेक्ट देना जरूरी है। यू नो वही हॉरर
The theme was podcasts. Yes, I remember. And
थीम पॉडकास्ट था। हां याद है मुझे। और
From somewhere it became Bhoot versus Bhairav.
कहीं से तो वो भूत वर्सेस भैरव बन गया।
Correct. Then talk of Tantra started coming up. And
सही। फिर तंत्रा की बातें निकलने लगी। और
After that chapter, the path of Tantra is known as the path of the gods.
उस चैप्टर के बाद तंत्र मार्ग को, देवताओं
I have to go to Sanatan Dharma. I have to go. I
को, सनातन धर्म को जाना है। जाना है। आई
I will tell you what I think about this chapter
विल टेल यू कि मैं इस चैप्टर के बारे में
Why am I talking now? we are my life
अब क्यों बात कर रहा हूं। हम मेरी जिंदगी
whatever happened in the last three months
में जो भी हुआ पिछले तीन महीनों में कहीं
Nor do I think that anything is as big as this
ना कहीं मुझे लगता है कि कुछ तो ये जितने
The two also had paranormal conversations
भी पैरानॉर्मल कन्वर्सेशंस करे थे दो-ती
He has had some effect over the years. And
सालों में उनका कुछ तो इफेक्ट रहा है। और
Because of that maybe from now on we will have
उस वजह से शायद अब से वी विल हैवली
Reduce Paranormal Conversations on the
रिड्यूस द पैरानॉर्मल कन्वर्सेशंस ऑन द
Show. And Talk More About Tantra Tantra or
शो। एंड टॉक मोर अबाउट तंत्र तंत्र या
Actually I wanted to talk to you because your
एक्चुअली आपसे बात इसलिए करनी थी कि आपकी
also switch on at some level same thing happened
भी स्विच ऑन सम लेवल ऐसी ही हुई इसी बात
But the question to you is that now at some point
पे बट सवाल आपसे ये है कि अब एट सम पॉइंट
In your spiritual journey I am sure that
इन योर स्पिरिचुअल जर्नी आई एम श्योर कि
Have you known Maa Kali, we are at least
आपने मां काली को जाना है हम हम एटलीस्ट
I will have to go, I don't know if I have worshipped
जाना होगा आई डोंट नो अगर उपासना करी है
Have you done it? Do you worship this Maa Kali?
आपने की है की है क्या आप इस मां काली की
Compare the worship with that chapter
उपासना को उस चैप्टर के साथ कंपेयर कर
when you deal with the oakley trail
सकते हो जब आप ऑकल ट्रेल के साथ डील कर
were staying. There is some linkage between oral trials and
रहे रहे थे। कुछ लिंकेज है ऑकल ट्रायल और
In the middle of Mahakali? C of Paranormal Research
महाकाली के बीच? सी पैरानॉर्मल रिसर्च की
if we talk then it is a very
अगर हम बात करें ना तो इट इज़ अ वेरी
dangerous state and let me tell you something that
डेंजरस स्टेट एंड लेट मी टेल यू समथिंग कि
if that is called sado science then there
अगर उसको सडो साइंस बोलते हैं ना तो देयर
There are reasons for it. Ok? because literally when
आर रीज़ंस फॉर इट। ठीक है? बिकॉज़ लिटरली जब
If we do paranormal research then we
हम लोग पैरानॉर्मल रिसर्च करते हैं तो वी
R beating the bush. something we didn't know
आर बीटिंग द बुश। कुछ हमें पता नहीं होता
What is in front is not there. Ok?
सामने क्या है नहीं है। ठीक है?
But paranormal research pushed me
लेकिन पैरानॉर्मल रिसर्च ने मुझे पुश किया
to come inu sadhna
टू कम इनू साधना
route. So once we investigate somewhere
मार्ग। तो एक बारी हम कहीं इन्वेस्टिगेशन
Were doing it and that investigation is over
कर रहे थे एंड वो इन्वेस्टिगेशन खत्म हुआ
And the second day I came to know that I had a cut
और सेकंड डे आई केम टू नो कि आई हैड अ कट
Mark on my thigh. and that was the cut mark
मार्क ऑन माय थाई। और वो जो कट मार्क था
That was painless. He didn't use pen.
दैट वास पेनलेस। वो पेन नहीं करता था।
From there our team decided that no, we
वहां से हमारी टीम ने तय किया कि नहीं हम
People we should go inu tantra way. Correct
लोगों को वी शुड गो इनू तंत्र मार्ग। ठीक
Is? And then why does it happen little by little?
है? और फिर थोड़ा-थोड़ा क्यों ऐसा?
Because you're not in paranormal research
क्योंकि पैरानॉर्मल रिसर्च में यू आर नॉट
Taught how to deal with entities. Ok? So
टॉट हाउ टू डील विद एंटिटीज। ठीक है? तो
One is to go on the path of sadhana even earlier
एक तो पहले से भी साधना मार्ग में जाने की
There was curiosity. what is the second if
उत्सुकता थी। दूसरा क्या है ना कि अगर
you will have to go on the path of sadhana, then that
आपको साधना मार्ग में जाना होगा ना तो वो
get you into it any way you can
आपको किसी भी तरीके से उसमें लेके आते हैं
that you have to come. Who brings it?
कि आपको आना ही है। कौन लेके आता है?
the deity you have been a devotee of, the one you
देवता जिनके आप साधक रहे हैं, जिनके आप
have been worshipers. Ok. so some incident happened
उपासक रहे हैं। ओके। तो कुछ इंसिडेंट हुआ
in your life because of which you
आपकी जिंदगी में जिसकी वजह से यू
understood or not let's figure out what
अंडरस्टुड कि नहीं लेट्स फिगर आउट व्हाट
we are dealing with what is the religious way out
वी आर डीलिंग व्हाट इज द रिलीजियस वे आउट
This is what you mean in paranormal
ये है क्या मतलब मतलब पैरानॉर्मल में यू
have equipments you can like that feel something
हैव एक्यूपमेंट्स यू कैन लाइक फील कि कुछ
So it is happening but in this tantra way you can see
तो हो रहा है बट इन तंत्र मार्ग यू कैन सी
what is happening this has happened with me
कि क्या हो रहा है दिस हैज़ हैपेंड विथ मी
I know ok when mommy casts an evil eye or someone else
आई नो ओके जब मम्मी नजर उतारती है या कोई
also take your eyes off me, what is actually happening
भी आपकी नजर उतार हम एक्चुअली हो रहा क्या
happens if a very negative person
होता है अगर कोई बहुत नकारात्मक व्यक्ति
Whose thoughts are very negative.
है जिसका थॉट्स बहुत नकार नकारात्मक है।
He always thinks negatively
वह बिल्कुल मतलब हमेशा नेगेटिव ही सोचता
It is about the people. such negative people
है लोगों के बारे में। ऐसे नेगेटिव लोगों
why thoughts manifest very quickly
का ना थॉट्स बड़ा जल्दी मैनिफेस्ट करता
Is. Very quickly. Like when on the path of sadhana
है। बड़ी जल्दी। जैसे जब साधना मार्ग में
If you move forward then I will tell you
आप आगे बढ़ेंगे ना तो आपको बताएंगे बताया
It will be told by your teachers that you should speak less.
जाएगा आपके गुरुओं के द्वारा कि कम बोलो।
Ok? What else? Think less. think less in
ठीक है? दूसरा क्या? कम सोचो। कम सोचो में
What? Think less negatively about yourself. You
क्या? अपने बारे में नेगेटिव कम सोचो। आप
If sadhana is on the path and you know about yourself
अगर साधना मार्ग में है और अपने बारे में
He will immediately think of negative things
नकारात्मक चीजें सोचेंगे वह तुरंत
Manifest does. You are something in your life
मैनिफेस्ट करता है। आप आपके लाइफ में कुछ
It is going to be positive. You think about that
पॉजिटिव होने वाला है। आप सोचिए उसके बारे
I am negative, it is like a straight line
में नेगेटिव वो बिल्कुल सीधी लकीर सा होने
The work that is to be done will be done in 10 parts. Correct
वाला काम जो है वो 10 भाग में होगा। ठीक
Isn't it? in the same way that negative people
है ना? उसी तरीके से जो नकारात्मक लोग
There are those who were earlier called witches.
होते हैं जिसको पहले विचेस बोला जाता था।
meaning not a witch like not a Wiccan but a witch who
मतलब नॉट विकन वाला विच नहीं ऐसे विच जो
They used to say it. So basically if he looks at you
बोलते थे। तो बेसिक वो आपको अगर देख लें
And don't think anything negative about you
और आपके बारे में कुछ नेगेटिव सोच ले ना
So your energy meaning is called metaphysics
तो आपका जो एनर्जी मतलब इसको मेटाफिजिक्स
You assume that this is a theory of metaphysics
आप मान लीजिए मेटाफिजिक्स का ये थ्योरी है
that the saw that is around you is yours
कि आपके आसपास जो आरा है ना आपका जो आपका
There is a field in which their energy shapes and mixes
फील्ड है उसमें उनका एनर्जी आकर के मिक्स
it happens and once that energy is in your
हो जाता है और एक बार जब वो एनर्जी आपके
If he comes inside then he will tell you according to his wish
अंदर आ गया तो वह अपने हिसाब से आपको
Then it means your thinking, your physical structure
फिर मतलब आपका सोचना आपका शारीरिक संरचना
If it changes it then what do we do
उसको चेंज करता है तो जब यह हम लोग क्या
When the bushes fall, what things do they use to shed them?
जब झाड़ झड़ते तो किन चीजों से झाड़ते
Are? They fall with lemon. It is acidic.
हैं? नींबू से झड़ते हैं। एसिडिक होता है।
So whatever that unwanted energy is, it will go away from that
तो वो जो भी अनवांटेड एनर्जी है वो उससे
It goes out.
निकल जाती है।
Ok. Can one ward off evil eye by worshipping goddess?
ओके। क्या देवी साधना करने से भी नजर
Can it be taken off? by herself who is the goddess
उतारी जा सकती है? खुद से जो देवी के
The seekers are not affected by evil eye. why is this
साधकों को नजर लगती ही नहीं है। यही क्यों
There is an armor form. Yes. any goddess
एक कवच फॉर्म होता है। हां। किसी भी देवी
By the practice of. By worshipping any goddess.
की साधना से। किसी भी देवी की साधना से।
Sadhana of Bhairava. Absolutely. of any deity
भैरव की साधना। बिल्कुल। किसी भी देवता की
You should do sadhana. If you worship God
आप साधना कर लें। अगर आप देवता की साधना
If you are doing it well then that God is yours
अच्छे से कर रहे हैं ना तो वह देवता आपके
live with. protects the seeker from external attacks
साथ रहते हैं। साधक को बाहरी अटैक से
One should not avoid one's own attacks too much.
ज्यादा ना खुद के अटैक से बचना चाहिए।
Ok? what happens to a seeker
ठीक है? एक साधक के साथ क्या होता है ना
When everything in life seems to be going so well
कि जीवन में जब सब बहुत अच्छा चलने लगता
isn't it then he starts thinking that this is this
है ना तब वह सोचना शुरू करता है कि ये ये
things are going well and these things are happening
चीजें अच्छी चल रही है और ये ये चीजें हो
Otherwise, this problem may occur in our life
जाए ना तो हमारे जीवन में ये ये खराबी हो
It can. It would be better if it doesn't happen.
सकती है। ना हो तो भला।
But as soon as the seeker thought about himself
लेकिन जैसे ही उस साधक ने अपने बारे में
did he manifest those things
उन चीजों को मैनिफेस्ट किया ना वह
in your life even in the slightest form
स्लाइटेस्ट फॉर्म में भी आपके लाइफ में
She returns. So this means a lot to a seeker
लौटती है। तो एक साधक को बहुत मतलब यह
It definitely happens with every seeker. what you
बिल्कुल होता है हर साधक के साथ। आपने जो
Negative Thoughts: Have you ever thought that
नेगेटिव थॉट्स कभी भी सोचा होगा ना वो
Manifest will do it. Positive also manifests
मैनिफेस्ट करेगा। पॉजिटिव भी मैनिफेस्ट
Will do it. Maybe this is also a human truth. But
करेगा। शायद यह एक ह्यूमन ट्रुथ भी है। पर
Manifestation of your thoughts by doing sadhna
साधना करने से आपके थॉट्स की मैनिफेस्टेशन
Ability is high. It becomes too much.
एबिलिटी ज्यादा। ज्यादा हो जाती है।
That is why just like we perform havan here, when
इसीलिए जैसे हवन करते हैं हमारे यहां जब
Do not open your mouth when havan is performed in Aghor
अघोर में हवन होता है तो मुंह नहीं खोलना
It happens. they don't talk even if you need something
होता है। दे नॉट टॉक इवन इफ यू नीड समथिंग
No, you tell me in gestures to bring that
ना आप इशारे में बोलते हो कि वो लाओ वो
Bring it. you can't say a word every word that
लाओ। यू कैन नॉट से अ वर्ड एव्री वर्ड दैट
This is set during Aghor Sadhna Havan
इज सेट ड्यूरिंग अघोर साधना हवन वो
It will be manifested. about someone
मैनिफेस्ट हो जाएगा। किसी के बारे में
Don't think bad. about someone
बुरा नहीं सोचना है। किसी के बारे में
Don't say anything bad. And you were right. These
बुरा नहीं बोलना है। और आपने सही बोला। ये
It happens for common people as well. a lot of people come
आम लोगों के लिए भी होता है। बहुत लोग आते
we have that our work is absolutely
हैं हमारे पास कि हमारा जो काम है बिल्कुल
It gets spoilt while being created. These were the people
बनता हुआ बिगड़ जाता है। यह वो लोग होते
Are you the one who thinks negatively about yourself?
हैं ना जो अपने बारे में नकारात्मक सोचते
Are. If any work is going to be done then its
हैं। कोई भी काम बनने वाला हो तो उसके
you will think about it 10 times if this happens
बारे में 10 बार सोचेंगे कि अगर यह होगा
So this work will not be done. That means absolutely 100%
तो यह काम नहीं हो पाएगा। मतलब एकदम 100%
yes, this work has to be done. But Than They Will Think
है यह काम हो जाना है। बट देन दे विल थिंक
That if this happens then it will not happen. It will happen.
कि ऐसा होगा तो नहीं होगा। ऐसा होगा।
Everything they think about themselves. now that
एवरीथिंग दे थिंक अबाउट देमसेल्फ। नाउ वो
It gradually manifests. things stop
धीरे-धीरे मैनिफेस्ट होता है। चीजें रुकनी
It starts in life. One more life
शुरू हो जाती है जीवन में। एक लाइफ और
I would like to say career oriented thing here. I
करियर ओरिएंटेड चीज कहना चाहूंगा यहां। आई
Think 99% of people are watching this podcast.
थिंक 99% ऑफ पीपल वाचिंग दिस पडकास्ट।
They also have materialistic goals
उनके भी मटेरियलिस्टिक गोल्स
Are. Often I have seen that those who are
हैं। अक्सर मैंने ये देखा कि जो लोग भैरव
Those who worship Shakti,
को पूजते हैं, जो लोग शक्ति को पूजते हैं,
Those sons have some materialistic
उन सों के कोई ना कोई मटेरियलिस्टिक
There are definitely quotas. doesn't mean that the
क्बिशंस तो होते हैं। डजंट मीन दैट द
Devotion is not there. Worship with devotion
भक्ति इज़ नॉट देयर। भक्ति के साथ पूजा
We do. What can we take from this career guidance
करते हैं। हम यह करियर गाइडेंस क्या ले
Can you? From Bhairav, from Shakti.
सकते हैं? भैरव से, शक्ति से।
Look, this is a topic that people don't understand yet
देखिए यह एक विषय ना अभी जो लोग नहीं समझ
A lot of people who are young right now are getting it
पा रहे हैं बहुत लोग अभी जो युवा है ना वह
Everyone is becoming a sanyasi after completing their studies
पढ़ाई लिखाई करके सब जो है सन्यासी बन रहे
Are. Ok? and according to them if he
हैं। ठीक है? और उनके हिसाब से अगर वह उस
worship goddess or gods in this way
तरीके से देवी भक्ति करें या फिर देवताओं
If they worship then they have the path
की भक्ति करें तो उनको जो मार्ग है उनका
It will be paved soon. People think like this don't they
जल्दी प्रशस्त होगा। ऐसा लोग सोचते हैं ना
that you wore a red dress, you wore a yellow dress
कि आपने लाल कपड़ा पहन लिया, आपने, पीला
You have worn the clothes, you have worn the fallen clothes
कपड़ा पहन लिया, आपने, गिरवा कपड़ा पहन
If you take it then you become a great devotee. And if you
लिया तो आप बड़े भक्त हो गए। और अगर आप
If you are wearing a shirt then you are a small devotee
शर्ट पहन पहन रहे हैं तो आप छोटे भक्त
Are. And you told me this last time too
हैं। और यह बात आपने पिछले बार भी मुझसे
asked if material desires are a
पूछा था कि क्या मटेरियल डिजायर्स एक
Is there hindrance in spiritual growth? Right?
हिंडरेंस है स्पिरिचुअल ग्रोथ में? राइट?
Something like that. No, it is not. this is the
समथिंग लाइक। नो, इट इज नॉट। दिस इज द
Plan of Mahamaya. Ok? we have such
प्लान ऑफ़ महामाया। ठीक है? हमारे यहां ऐसे
There have been saints who have been saints since childhood.
संत हुए हैं जो कि बाल्यकाल से संत हैं।
In his childhood, he was given a
उनको बचपन में उनके माता-पिता ने किसी
Whatever is there in the ashram is given to them
आश्रम में जो है दे दिया तो उनके लिए
Mahamaya had decided that he would be a saint
महामाया ने यह तय किया था कि वो संत ही
or someone who is in a very unconscious state
रहे या कोई बहुत अबोध स्थिति में जो है
He felt that he had to attain God. For him
उसको लगा कि भगवत प्राप्ति करनी है। उसको
Mahamaya has decided and sent you to go now
महामाया ने तय करके भेजा है कि तुम जाओ अब
whatever this life of yours is
जो है तुम्हारा यह जो भी जीवन है इसमें
You have to attain the gods. You
तुमको देवताओं की प्राप्ति करनी है। तुम
Whatever it is, move away from this life. But the one who
जो है इस जीवन से हट जाओ। लेकिन जो एक
In the household religion, a person is his first
गृहस्थ धर्म में व्यक्ति है उसका पहला
The aim is that he should completely save the household
उद्देश्य है कि वह गृहस्ती को पूर्ण रूप
live by it and only then what is
से निर्वाह करें और उसके बाद ही जो है
What do you call that which is your own in religion?
उसको क्या कहते हैं धर्म में जो है अपना
time should be given and to the gods who
समय देना चाहिए और देवताओं के प्रति जो
Keep the feeling you have and tell it to the gods
भाव है वह भाव रखें और देवताओं को यह बोलो
You decide what is best for us
कि जो हमारे लिए सबसे अच्छा है वो आप तय
Do it.
कीजिए।
ok to
ओके टू
summarize a i think you are saying that a
समराइज अ आई थिंक आप यह कह रहे हो कि एक
There is a path of human life. First you
ह्यूमन लाइफ का पाथ होता है। पहले आपको
about yourself about your family
खुद के फैमिली के बारे में खुद के बारे
I first think about my own comfort
में खुद के कंफर्ट के बारे में पहले उन
Attention should be paid to all things. and if
सारी चीजों पर ध्यान देना चाहिए। और अगर
Your heart desires to move forward in Sadhana
साधना में आगे जाने की इच्छा है आपके दिल
I should request the daughter to
में तो डेटी से रिक्वेस्ट करना चाहिए कि
Take me to that. the one who is your date
टेक मी टू दैट। जो आपके डेटी है ना वो
will pave your way. all the same
आपका मार्ग प्रशस्त करेंगे। वही सारे
I will make arrangements. Let us assume 12 from today 10
व्यवस्था करेंगे। मान के चलिए 12 आज से 10
years ago or when we only knew Durga
साल पहले या फिर जब हम सिर्फ दुर्गा
Used to recite Saptashati. We knew a little about
सप्तशती करते थे। हमें थोड़ी पता था हम
You will become a seeker. We have lived a life of our own
साधक बन जाएंगे। हमने तो अपना एक जीवन
began. I studied mass communication
शुरू किया। हमने मास कम्युनिकेशन की पढ़ाई
of. We worked in newspapers. We
की। हमने अखबारों में नौकरी किया। हमने
Worked at UNICEF and did whatever.
यूनिसेफ में नौकरी किया और जो भी किया।
Remained in politics for a few days. we never
कुछ दिन पॉलिटिक्स में रहे। हमें कभी नहीं
Did you know what we said? absolutely
पता था कि हम क्या कहते हैं? बिल्कुल ही
We will follow the path of religion. But the gods
धर्म के मार्ग पे चल देंगे। लेकिन देवताओं
has turned our lives in such a way that we
ने इस तरीके से जीवन को मोड़ा कि हम अपने
Came into the path of sadhana. and just as much as
साधना मार्ग में आ गए। और अभी जितना
The more we pay attention to the gods, the more we
देवताओं पर हम ध्यान देते हैं उतना ही हम
Also pay attention to your household. Any
अपनी गृहस्ती पर भी ध्यान देते हैं। किसी
But even if we are paying less attention to it
पर भी अगर हम कम ध्यान दे रहे हैं इसका
Meaning we are not right with our religion
मतलब हम अपने धर्म के साथ सही नहीं
because the first religion which we get
क्योंकि हमें पहला धर्म जो हमें जिसका
We have to follow the Dharma of the household
अनुसरण हमें करना है वो गृहस्थ धर्म का
Is. Or else we should become sannyasis. Everything
है। हम या फिर हम सन्यासी हो जाएं। सब कुछ
Leave it, don't do that, become a fugitive
छोड़छाड़ दें, भगोड़े बन जाए वो नहीं करना
Needed Is it okay? Wood you say that the monk
चाहिए। ठीक है ना? वुड यू से कि सन्यासी
The core logic behind its creation is that
बनने के पीछे कोर लॉजिक यही रहता है कि
We have to progress in our sadhana quickly. Meaning
साधना में आगे बढ़ना है जल्दी से। मतलब
The core logic of speed remains.
स्पीड का कोर लॉजिक रहता है।
See now when you talk to the sannyasis
देखिए अभी जब आप सन्यासियों से बात करेंगे
Nor would those people make fun of this thing
ना तो वह लोग भी इस चीज का मजाक उड़ाते
Are. Now, there is too much renunciation happening.
हैं। अब सन्यास बहुत ज्यादा हो रहा है।
If you ask the sanyasis why so many
सन्यासियों से अगर आप पूछेंगे ना कि इतने
The number of sannyasis who are girl sannyasis is increasing
सन्यासी बढ़ रहे हैं जो बालिकाले सन्यासी
He will tell you there are four types of sannyasis
वो आपको बताएंगे चार तरह के सन्यासी होते
Are. Ok?
हैं। ठीक है?
First
पहले
Sanyasis who do not wish to work, they
सन्यासी जिनको काम नहीं करना है तो वह
become a sanyasi. do some work
सन्यासी बन जाते हैं। कुछ काम करते हैं
They keep getting food. Other sannyasis
उनको भोजन मिलता रहता है। दूसरे सन्यासी
He who is suffering from the household, he is suffering from his wife
जो गृहस्थ से पीड़ित हैं, वह बीवी से
Are you upset or are you troubled by your family members?
परेशान है या अपने घर वालों से परेशान है,
He retires. The third monk who
वह सन्यास ले लेते हैं। तीसरे सन्यासी जो
He has fled after committing a crime and has become a sadhu
क्राइम करके भागे हुए हैं, वह साधु बन
They go so that the police cannot catch them.
जाते हैं ताकि पुलिस उनको पकड़ नहीं पाए।
And there is a very small section of Sanyas Ashram
और एक बहुत छोटा तबका है सन्यास आश्रम का
which is really just like nurturing the gods
जो कि सच में बिल्कुल ही देवताओं को पालने
He retires for the sake of it. This is a very small
के लिए सन्यास लेता है। यह एक बहुत छोटा
There is a section that will be available
तबका है जो मिलेगा
No. The rest is meant for us
नहीं। बाकी जो है वो मतलब हमारे एक
Gurudev was a saint. He said what
गुरुदेव थे सन्यासी थे। उन्होंने बोला जो
If it didn't happen to your family, it will happen to you.
अपने परिवार का नहीं हुआ तुम्हारा होगा।
He said a big thing while laughing
बड़ी बात उन्होंने बोली थी हंसते हुए
But you can understand what a big deal he is
लेकिन आप समझो कि उन्होंने कितनी बड़ी बात
She said and even the sanyasis say this
बोली और यह बात सन्यासी लोग भी बोलते
What? Not every sannyasi is such that you
क्या? हर सन्यासी ऐसा नहीं होता कि आप
I should bow down and pay obeisance to him. Very little
दंडवत प्रणाम कर जाए उनके सामने। बहुत कम
The Sanyasis are those who are from childhood. For them
सन्यासी ऐसे हैं जो बाल्यकाल के हैं। उनको
Looking at you, this feeling will come that is there. For them
आपको देख कर के जो है ऐसा भाव आएगा। उनको
After seeing him you will understand that he is a sannyasi.
देख के आपको समझ में आएगा ये सन्यासी हैं।
Now we will talk about that timeline
अब हम बात करेंगे वो टाइमलाइन के बारे
In. We are going to tell you about the timeline of the 10 Mahavidyas.
में। हम अ 10 महाविद्या की टाइमलाइन
Actually let's boil it down completely. Gin
एक्चुअली एकदम बॉयल्ड डाउन करते हैं। जिन
People have also heard about 10 Mahavid
लोगों ने 10 महाविद के बारे में सुना भी
No, let's start from there. Good
नहीं है वहां से शुरुआत करते हैं। अच्छा
Chapter Zero I think it's a no. Very nice.
चैप्टर जीरो आई थिंक इट्सेंट। वेरी नाइस।
Ok. See what is there about 10 Mahavidyas
ओके। देखिए क्या है कि 10 महाविद के बारे
There is a lot of confusion in me. Ok. 10
में ना बहुत भ्रांति है। ठीक है। 10
This is true about Mahavidya. is mahavid
महाविद के बारे में यह सही है। महाविद है
Different chapters of knowledge or evolution
अलग-अलग चैप्टर्स ऑफ नॉलेज या इवोल्यूशन
of knowledge like the 10th avatar of the human
ऑफ नॉलेज जैसे 10 अवतार का जो ह्यूमन
it's about evolution in the same way
इवोल्यूशन के बारे में है उसी तरीके से यह
Knowledge or enlightenment of your brain
नॉलेज या आपका जो ब्रेन का एनलाइटमेंट है
It is about him. but 10 great scholars
उसके विषय में होता है। लेकिन 10 महाविद
one who understands where the origin of
का प्रादुर्भाव कहां हुआ यह समझने वाला
The thing is. He who knows that story
बात है। वो जो उस कथा को जो जानता है वो
Knows the importance of 10 Mahavidyas
जानता है कि 10 महाविद का क्या महत्व है
In life. Ok? Now we have named Durga
जीवन में। ठीक है? अभी हमने दुर्गा का नाम
I took Bhagwati’s. End of Durga Saptashati
लिया भगवती का। दुर्गा सप्तशती के अंत
When I complete 13 chapters then
में जब 13 अध्याय पूरे हो जाते हैं ना तो
Bhagwati says in the end that now my
भगवती अंत में बोलती है कि अब मेरा
To kill the inaccessible demon
प्रादुर्भाव दुर्गम राक्षस के वध के लिए
And then I'll be Durga Durga
होगा और उसके बाद मैं दुर्गा दुर्गा
I will tell you, understand that we have written 13 chapters
कहलाऊंगी समझो बात वो 13 अध्याय हमने
I read Durga Saptashati and at last Bhagwati
दुर्गा सप्तशती का पढ़ लिया अंत में भगवती
said now my name will be Durga when I
ने बोला अब मेरा नाम दुर्गा होगा जब मैं
It is about the timeline, I didn't
यह टाइमलाइन का जो बात है ना कि मैंने
He said, time is stagnant so first of all Bhagwati
बोला टाइम स्टैगेंट है तो भगवती का पहले
In that book the name was written as Durga
उस किताब में पहले जैसे नाम दुर्गा लिखा
It has happened. In the 13th chapter of that book, Bhagwati
हुआ है। उस किताब के 13व अध्याय में भगवती
It says that when the Durgam demon is killed
बोलती है कि जब दुर्गम राक्षस का वध
If I do it then I will be called Durga. This is the Durga
करूंगी तब दुर्गा कहलाऊंगी। यह जो दुर्गा
It was from there that the 10 Mahavidyas emerged
का प्रादुर्भाव हुआ ना वहीं से 10 महाविद
There came into being. of the inaccessible monster
का प्रादुर्भाव हुआ। दुर्गम राक्षस का
Arrival took place. It was very austere and inaccessible
आगमन हुआ। बहुत तपस्वी था और दुर्गम
The demon took a boon from Lord Brahma that
राक्षस ने ब्रह्मा जी से वर ले लिया कि
All the knowledge about the earth should come to me.
सारा नॉलेज जो धरती का वो मेरे पास आ जाए।
Ok? So the inaccessible monster has the rest
ठीक है? तो दुर्गम राक्षस के पास बाकी
Apart from having knowledge, the four Vedas are also
नॉलेज होने के अलावा जो चार वेद है वह भी
became his slaves. Ok? So the earth which
उसके गुलाम हो गए। ठीक है? तो पृथ्वी जो
Isn't it so? She has become disinterested in knowledge. Earth
है ना वह ज्ञान से विरक्त हो गई। पृथ्वी
But there is no knowledge left and there is chaos
पर कहीं ज्ञान ही नहीं बचा और त्राहिमाम
Done. Meaning in Devlok everyone is like an animal
हो गया। देवलोक में मतलब सब जानवर जैसा
Started doing it. Started living like animals. Complete
करने लगे। जानवरों की तरह रहने लगे। पूरा
Meaning that the entire creation is going to be destroyed
मतलब जो पूरी सृष्टि का जो है विनाश होने
Put. What will happen without knowledge? So the god
लगा। ज्ञान के बिना क्या होगा? तो देवता
who went to Brahma ji and said that you
जो है गए ब्रह्मा जी के पास और बोले कि आप
Has he given this boon? then goddess
ने क्या यह वर दे दिया है? तो फिर भगवती
These people appealed to the same
का इन लोगों ने आवाहन किया वही
From the sources. Ok? and the Bhagawati
स्त्रोत्रों से। ठीक है? और भगवती ने
Took the form of Durga. Ok? and Durga's
दुर्गा का रूप लिया। ठीक है? और दुर्गा का
After taking the form of Durgam, he killed the demon
रूप लेने के बाद दुर्गम राक्षस के वध के
for 10 more goddesses apart from Durga
लिए दुर्गा से 10 और देवियों का
An outbreak occurred. who together made the inaccessible
प्रादुर्भाव हुआ। जिन्होंने मिलके दुर्गम
Killed the demon. his his whole
राक्षस का वध किया। उसका उसका पूरे
Destroyed the empire and all four Vedas
साम्राज्य का संहार किया और चारों वेद
I brought it back from them. So when he came back with the Vedas
उनसे वापस ले आए। तो जब वेद ले वापस आए तो
the knowledge which had vanished from the world
जो दुनिया से ज्ञान चला गया था ना जो
Vidya had gone away, she has come back. that's why
विद्या चली गई थी वह वापस आ गई। इसीलिए
These are called Mahavidya. Vedas to the world
इनको महाविद्या कहते हैं। वेद दुनिया को
Durga's 10 incarnations
देने के लिए दुर्गा का 10 अवतारों में
Appearance took place and Vedas were those 10 incarnations
प्रादुर्भाव हुआ और वेद वो 10 जो अवतार थी
She brought it back and Gyan came back. that's why
वो वापस ले आई और ज्ञान वापस आए। इसीलिए
Mahavidya is okay, right? So black is the first one in that
महाविद्या ठीक है ना? तो उसमें काली पहली
Tara then Tripura Sundari then Bhuvaneshwari
तारा फिर त्रिपुरा सुंदरी फिर भुवनेश्वरी
Chinmastika Matangi. She is Matangi. Yes.
छिन्मस्तिका मातंगी। मातांगी है। हां।
After that Baglamukhi
उसके बाद बगलामुखी
Is. Matangi is the ninth Mahavidya. so this
है। मातांगी नौवीं महाविद्या है। तो ये
There were different Mahavidyas. So Kali's work
अलग-अलग महाविद्याएं हुई। तो काली का काम
is to give birth as I told you. Tara's
है जन्म देना जैसा मैंने बताया। तारा का
The job is to impart knowledge. in a person's life
काम है ज्ञान देना। एक इंसान के जीवन में
of their hearts and minds
उनके दिल और दिमाग के
What is the role of these 10 Mahavidyas inside?
अंदर ये 10 महाविद का रोल क्या रहता है?
In a human journey. 10 Mahavidya Sadhak's
एक ह्यूमन जर्नी में। 10 महाविद साधक के
When you do sadhna in life and Bhagwati
जीवन में जब आप साधना करते हैं और भगवती
If you do sadhna of this then you will get knowledge of all the ten Mahavidyas
की साधना करते हैं तो आपको दसों महाविद को
One has to live. Ok? So black is black
जीना होता है। ठीक है? तो काली जो है काली
What is? Kali with Mahadev of Mahakal
क्या है? काली महादेव के साथ महाकाल के
She sits together. He is fierce. Ok? and two more
साथ विराजती है। वो घोर है। ठीक है? और दो
It is extreme. one black and one
एक्सट्रीम होता है। एक काली का और एक
Of Tripura Sundari. Both are black. As
त्रिपुरा सुंदरी का। दोनों काली है। जैसे
We know Kala Bhairava and Gora Bhairava. We
हम लोग काला भैरव गोरा भैरव जानते हैं। हम
Similarly, one of them is black and the other is white
वैसे ही ये एक एक काली है और एक गोरी काली
Is. Is it okay? So Kali when you meditate
है। ठीक है ना? तो काली आप जब साधना
When Kali comes into the area and casts her eyes on you
क्षेत्र में आए काली का आप पे जब दृष्टि
If you read it, you are born in the system.
पड़ा तो आपका तंत्र में जन्म हो जाता है।
Ok? Then you come to the second stage.
ठीक है? उसके बाद आप दूसरे स्टेज में आते
Yes, Tara is coming. Tara's job is for you
हैं तारा आती है। तारा का काम है आपके
Cutting off past karmas. Ok? Who
पिछले कर्मों को काट देना। ठीक है? जो
You have knots to cut and you will gain knowledge
आपके नॉट्स हैं उसको काटना और आपको ज्ञान
Give. Is it okay? then come in third
देना। ठीक है ना? उसके बाद तीसरे में आते
Ah Tripura Sundari. which means all three
हैं अह त्रिपुरा सुंदरी। जो तीनों मतलब
It is considered the most beautiful among the people. He
लोक है उसमें सबसे सुंदर मानी जाती है। वह
You have the most beautiful looks and the most beautiful mind
आपको सबसे सुंदर रूप और सबसे सुंदर दिमाग
They give. Ok? Then comes Bhuvaneshwari.
देती हैं। ठीक है? फिर आती है भुवनेश्वरी।
She expands that opulence.
वो उस ऐश्वर्य का विस्तार करती हैं।
Chinmastika comes again and what you have till today
छिन्मस्तिका फिर आती हैं और जो आज तक आपने
Learning destroys it. Isn't it a beheading?
सीखा उसका नाश कर देती है। बीहेड है ना
Whoremastika. The fierce Chandika has raised her neck
छिनमस्तिका। प्रचंड चंडिका ने अपना गर्दन
Cut it off. So what do they say there?
काट दिया। तो वो वहां पर क्या कहते हैं?
It destroys your ego. Then
आपका जो ईगो है उसको खत्म करती है। फिर
Bhairavi comes who is your enemy
आती है भैरवी जो कि जो आपके एनिमीज़ है
It destroys him. Yours in the first
उसको डिस्ट्रॉय करती है। पहले में आपका
I have destroyed your ego
आपका जो ईगो है उसको खत्म किया छिन
Mastika cut off the head and then Bhairavi came
मस्तिका ने मस्तक काट के और फिर भैरवी आई
And they destroyed everything else. Correct
और उन्होंने बाकी सब डिस्ट्रॉय किया। ठीक
Is? then in the same order as
है? उसके बाद इसी क्रम में जो
Yes, Dhumavati is coming. that too of destruction
है धूमावती आती हैं। वो भी डिस्ट्रक्शन की
Devi and Baglamukhi come. Dhumavati to you
देवी और बगलामुखी आती हैं। धूमावती आपको
It revives and the one who is Baglamukhi
पुनर्जीवित करती हैं और जो बगलामुखी है वो
determines that whatever elements are around you
तय करती है कि आपके आसपास जो भी ऐसे तत्व
These are the things that prevent you from becoming a successful seeker now
हैं जो आपको अब सफल साधक बनने से रोके
May they be destroyed. That is the final stage. Then
उनका नाश हो जाए। वो अंतिम स्टेज है। फिर
Matangi comes. Matangi teaches you again
आती है मातांगी। मातांगी आपको पुनः विद्या
She gives it. the knowledge that was lost when
देती है। वह विद्या जो लुप्त हो गया था जब
Chhin Mastika had broken you. Ok? And
छिन मस्तिका ने आपको तोड़ा था। ठीक है? और
In the end comes Mahalakshmi Kamala who will bless you
अंत में आती है महालक्ष्मी कमला जो आपको
takes you back to the same glory you were in
फिर से उसी वैभव पर ले जाती है जिस पर आप
Were in the beginning. Ok? it is also called Garuda yoga
शुरुआत में थे। ठीक है? इसको गरुड़ योग भी
They say. What is of the eagle which is of the phoenix
कहते हैं। गरुड़ का क्या है जो फिनिक्स का
it is a concept or not it is the same concept
कांसेप्ट है ना सेम कांसेप्ट होता है
that the eagle dies and rises again
गरुड़ का कि गरुड़ मर जाता है और फिर से
He is alive. so in human life
वो जीवित होता है। तो इंसान के जीवन में
This Garuda Yoga brings you great height
ये गरुड़ योग आता है कि आप एकदम हाइट में
will stay and then fall again
रहेंगे उसके बाद गिरेंगे उसके बाद फिर से
Will get up. or who will rise a second time then fall
उठेंगे। या जो दूसरी बार उठेंगे फिर गिरना
Does not happen. what am I not able to do in office
नहीं होता है। ये क्या मुझे ऑफिस में नहीं
should keep?
रखना चाहिए?
do you think its negative energy because i
डू यू थिंक इट्स नेगेटिव एनर्जी बिकॉज़ आई
have had a Kali worshipper come and
हैव हैड एक एक काली उपासक आए थे और
He said hey the skull is of Kali
उन्होंने कहा कि अरे कपाल तो काली की
We are my favourites but I don't know especially
फेवरेट होती है हम बट आई डोंट नो एस्पेशली
after this face I don't keep such things
आफ्टर दिस फेस ऐसी चीजें नहीं रखूं रखूं
How do you feel? Are they affecting you?
हाउ डू यू फील आप इनसे अफेक्ट होता है
Am I not affected by these decorations?
क्या मैं अफेक्ट नहीं होता मुझे ये सजाने
I feel like I'm not affected
का सामान लग रहा है आई एम नॉट अफेक्टेड
yes that's it it doesn't affect so it's about
हां वही इट डज नॉट अफेक्ट सो इट्स अबाउट
what you put into art basically it is a
व्हाट यू पुट इंटू आर्ट बेसिकली इट इज़ अ
Art hum that's how I look at it. yes it is
आर्ट हम दैट्स हाउ आई लुक एट इट। यस इट इज
everything will start affecting in your
एवरीथिंग विल स्टार्ट अफेक्टिंग इन योर
Life. Then it will become difficult to live. We every
लाइफ। तब तो जीना मुश्किल हो जाएगा। हम हर
You will keep thinking about the thing. From this
चीज के बारे में आप सोचते रहेंगे। इससे
This is happening to me, that is happening to me.
मेरे साथ ऐसा हो रहा है, वैसा हो रहा है।
Each person has his own interpretation
हम हर एक व्यक्ति का एक अपना इंटरप्रिटेशन
Is. The head of Bhagwati Kali is the favourite
है। भगवती काली का मुंड जो है वो फेवरेट
Is. There is nothing like that. Yes. Ok.
है। ऐसा कुछ है नहीं। हां। ठीक है।
When Kali does Tantra Sadhna
काली जब तंत्र साधना करते हैं
No, then we would have given Kali a seat on our heads
ना, तो काली को आसन हम लोग मुंड पे देते
Are. It has a prescribed format that
हैं। उसका एक प्रिस्राइब फॉर्मेट है कि इस
In this way you bring that head.
तरीके से वो जो मुंड है उसको आप लाते हैं।
Whatever ghost is there then it would be invoked
उसमें फिर जो भी प्रेत है उसका आवाहन होता
and then we place Bhagvati on top of it
है और फिर उसके ऊपर भगवती को हम लोग रखते
Are. That's all the head is used for. Ok
हैं। इतना ही मुंड का प्रयोग होता है। ओके
shaved nothing that needs to be shown
मुंडा ऐसा कुछ नहीं कि दिखाने की चीजें
or are you on the wrong path of wandering
हैं या फिर ले घूमने के अघोर मार्ग में
There are three seekers. it had a skull
तीन साधक होते हैं। उसमें एक कपालिक होता
Is. So the one who is Kapalika is made from skulls
है। तो जो कपालिक होता है वो कपालों से
He does sadhana. This is called skull. So
साधना करता है। इसको कपाल बोलते हैं। तो
Cranial activities take place. one is the skull
कपाल क्रियाएं होती हैं। एक तो कपाल
Not the rituals which are performed on dead bodies.
क्रिया जो डेड बॉडी पे होती है वो नहीं।
There are skull operations in which
कपाल क्रियाएं होती है जिसमें कपाल में ही
All powers are surrendered. Means it
सारी शक्तियों को विरा जाता है। मतलब इट
Just like we use memory cards now
इज जैसे अभी हम लोग मेमोरी कार्ड यूज़ करते
Yes, it is kept in that manner. all
हैं उस तरीके से उसको रखा जाता है। सारी
sadhanas are offered there and
साधनाओं को वहां अर्पित किया जाता है और
goddess above him
उसके ऊपर भगवती
The ka is established. Therefore, the skull
का को स्थापित किया जाता है। इसलिए कपाल
It is important. Ok.
महत्वपूर्ण है। ओके।
But this is obviously not an actual skull. These
पर ये ऑब्वियसली एक्चुअल स्कल नहीं है। ये
Maybe it's made of POP, I don't know from what?
शायद पता नहीं किससे हां पीओपी से बना हुआ
Is. But because it is made in this shape
है। बट क्योंकि इस शेप में बना हुआ इस शेप
Because of this the energy gets affected. any of the
की वजह से एनर्जी अफेक्ट होती है। किसी भी
Cheese does not have an energy effect on you
चीज से एनर्जी इफेक्ट नहीं होती आपके खुद
Apart from the mind of. no the same veg non veg one
के मन के अलावा। नहीं वही वेज नॉनवेज वाला
The logic is the same that eating it does not have any effect
लॉजिक वही कि खाने से जैसे इफेक्ट नहीं हो
could you mean any material like that
सकता वैसे ही किसी सामग्री से आपका मतलब
There can be no interest or no interest. we our
कोई हित या हित नहीं हो सकता है। हम हमारे
Guruji is the one who taught us so much when we were beginners
गुरु जी हैं उन्होंने हमें जब हम शुरुआती
When we were in the period of sadhana then we
साधनाओं के दौर में थे ना तो हम हमें आप
By looking at this one could understand the Tantra of the path
देख के समझ सकते थे ये तंत्र मार्ग का
There is a person. because it's all in our hands
व्यक्ति है। क्योंकि हमारे पूरे हाथ में
Something was always tied. Something used to be tied here.
कुछ बंधा रहता था। कुछ यहां बंधा रहता था।
Used to wear garlands.
मालाएं पहनते थे।
So they asked me why are you doing this so much
तो उन्होंने हमसे पूछा यह आप इतना क्यों
do you wear it? So we told them that this is us
पहनते हैं? तो हमने उनको बोला कि यह हम
Wear it for your protection. This is ours
अपनी सुरक्षा के लिए पहनते हैं। यह हमारा
It is an amulet. You should assume that. So he
ताबीज है। ऐसा मान लो आप। तो उन्होंने
He said that this is not the talisman of a seeker. of the seeker
बोला साधक का ताबीज यह नहीं होता। साधक का
This is the amulet. where a seeker sits
ताबीज यह होता है। एक साधक जहां बैठ जाए
There is no negative energy there
वहां पे नकारात्मक ऊर्जा होनी ही नहीं
Needed So if you are wearing it yourself then
चाहिए। तो आप ही खुद पहन रहे हैं तो फिर
What will you protect the rest of us from? What
आप बाकियों की क्या सुरक्षा करेंगे? क्या
Will you meet the powers that be? so today is that day
आप शक्तियों से मिलेंगे? तो वो दिन है आज
It is the day of. We don't wear anything that
का दिन है। हम कुछ भी ऐसा नहीं पहनते जो
that from the security point of view
कि सुरक्षा तंत्र के दृष्टिकोण से बहुत
Be important. The same way we treat everyone
महत्वपूर्ण हो। हम उसी तरीके से सबको
Should become a talisman. Ok? external
ताबीज बन जाना चाहिए। ठीक है? बाहरी
Energy: Nothing can disturb you.
एनर्जी कुछ भी आपको डिस्टर्ब ना कर सके।
You should be that strong. The seeker especially
यू शुड बी दैट स्ट्रांग। साधक तो खास करके
He has so much faith in his Guru and the East
उनको अपने गुरु और ईस्ट पे इतना भरोसा
It should be that when they are there then no one can control us
होना चाहिए कि जब वो हैं तो हम पे कोई भी
Energy that is not work
ऊर्जा जो है काम नहीं
will do it. Stay safe. no different for him
करेगी। सुरक्षित रहिएगा। उसके लिए कोई अलग
There is no need to recite the mantras.
से मंत्र विधान करने की आवश्यकता नहीं है।
What does Maa Kali want from her devotees?
मां काली अपने भक्तों से क्या चाहती है?
Mother Kali wants this from her devotees
मां काली अपने भक्तों से यह चाहती है कि
May you attain nirvana sin. you everything
आप निर्वाण पाप प्राप्त करें। आप सब कुछ
Learn to do so. Everyone should understand this. Ok? that's why
को सीख लें। सब समझ लें। ठीक है? इसीलिए
Maya's job is to take you to Mahadev
माया का काम है कि आपको महादेव तक ले
Go. Maya was born in this game
जाना। माया का प्रादुर्भाव हुआ था इस खेल
in order to create so that the living beings who are souls
को रचने के लिए ताकि जो जीव आत्माएं हैं
Nor could he understand what their purpose was.
ना वह समझ सके कि उनका प्रयोजन क्या है।
So as long as they are given different tasks, today's language
तो जब तक उनको अलग-अलग टास्क आज की भाषा
I speak. that task will not be done
में बोलते हैं। वह टास्क नहीं कराया जाएगा
Until then he will not understand what is not
तब तक वह समझ नहीं पाएगा कि क्या है नहीं
Is. What is the balance of the universe? So the goddess
है। क्या बैलेंस है सृष्टि का। तो भगवती
Kali's only purpose is to make you
काली का सिर्फ यही उद्देश्य है कि वह आपको
will take you to the path from where you can reach Mahadev
उस मार्ग पर ले जाएगी जहां से आप महादेव
It should reach till. I love them very much
तक पहुंच जाए। उनसे मेरा लगाव बहुत ज्यादा
has increased a lot lately we mean
बढ़ा है हाल ही में बहुत ज्यादा हम मतलब
If I get a little emotional right now I
अगर मैं अभी इमोशनली थोड़ा बह जाऊं मैं
I will start crying that much I am feeling affection
रोने लगूंगा उतना ज्यादा लगाव फील हो रहा
we are with them so I will not talk to them
है उनसे हम हम इसलिए मैं नहीं बात करूंगा
more about that attachment when we
उस लगाव के बारे में ज्यादा हमारा जब
When sadhana started we became Tara
साधना का शुरुआत हुआ था तो हम तारा
He was practicing Maha Vidya but Tara
महाविद्या की साधना कर रहे थे लेकिन तारा
we were not able to prove it okay so
हमें सिद्ध नहीं हो रही थी ठीक है तो जिन
We just talked about Guruji, right?
गुरु जी की अभी हमने बात किया ना उन्होंने
Then he gave us a mantra of Kali and that
फिर हमें एक मंत्र दिया काली का और उस
Only by mantras and not by miracles in my life
मंत्र से ही मेरे जीवन में ना चमत्कार से
Interview
साक्षात्कार
It happened and when we caught Kali then Tara
हुआ और जब काली को हमने पकड़ा तो फिर तारा
we were also able to catch us and
भी हमें हम पकड़ पाए और
Then our journey continues till Bhairav ​​ji
फिर भैरव जी तक हमारा जो है सफर आगे जारी
remained. Five of its 10 Mahavidyas
रहा। उसके 10 महाविद में पांच महाविद्या
of this from Tantra and the rest from Sri Vidya
का तंत्र से और बाकी श्री विद्या से हमने
Completed the sadhana. Explain that when the mother
साधना पूरा किया। यह समझाइए कि जब मां
What happens when Kali comes into your life? So
काली आपकी जिंदगी में आए तो हुआ क्या? तो
Bhagwati Kali, that is birth, that is time and
भगवती काली जो है ना वह जन्म है वह काल और
Black darkness, great void, everything is right from there
काली अंधकार महाशून्य ठीक है वहीं से सब
If we start, then we start with Bhagwati Kali only
शुरुआत होता है तो भगवती काली से ही हमारा
Tantra also started when for the first time something
भी तंत्र का शुरुआत हुआ जब पहला बार कुछ
did not understand that we were doing something
समझ में आया ना कि हम कुछ कर रहे हैं जब
If you come into Tantra Sadhna in the beginning then
शुरुआत में आप तंत्र साधना में आएंगे तो
You won't understand anything for three-four years
आपको कुछ नहीं समझ में आएगा तीन-चार साल
So it is blank, you won't feel anything, why?
तो इट इज़ ब्लैंक कुछ नहीं लगेगा क्यों कर
we are not able to understand any difference
रहे हैं हम कोई अंतर नहीं समझ में आ रहा
you will become a bit aggressive which means
है आप थोड़ा अग्रेसिव हो जाएंगे मतलब जो
They say there is some value addition in life
बोलते हैं ना कुछ वैल्यू एडिशन लाइफ में
do not seem. v is why it's not too
नहीं दिखता है। वि इज व्हाई इट्सेंट टू
Enjoy the process. Yes yes, just enjoy it.
एंजॉय द प्रोसेस। यस यस एंजॉय करो बस बस।
So when I was doing sadhna of Kali Bhagwati then
तो जब काली भगवती की साधना कर रहा था तो
For the first time I felt that our
पहली बार मुझे अनुभूति हुआ कि नहीं हमारा
The mantra is awakening or our goddess
मंत्र जो है वो जग रहा है या भगवती हमारे
Is with me. We had gone to a place to perform havan. So
साथ है। हम एक जगह पर हवन करने गए थे। तो
That too was a Nath family. But to us he
वह भी नाथों का परिवार था। लेकिन हमसे वह
There was a little enthai. So there was a pyre. over there
थोड़ा एंटाई था। तो एक चिता थी। वहां पर
The havan was being performed. So those people have a lot of
हवन हो रहा था। तो उन लोगों ने बहुत
The material was collected and kept. Us
सामग्री इकट्ठा करके रखी थी। हमें
We were invited to perform havan but we
निमंत्रण दिया था हवन करने का लेकिन हमें
The material was not provided. Gave very little. so he
सामग्री नहीं दी थी। बहुत कम दिया। तो वह
If you were doing your havan then you were doing havan
अपना हवन कर रहे थे तो हवन कर रहे थे
So they are throwing one material after another into the pyre
तो एक से एक सामग्री चिता में फेंक रहे
Were. But the pyre was not burning. that means
थे। लेकिन चिता जल नहीं रही थी। वो मतलब
That doesn't happen. very last stage water
वो नहीं होता। एकदम लास्ट स्टेज वाला जल
Had been. And a lot of the fuss that happens is smoking
रहा था। और बहुत सारा जो रार होता है धूमन
It happens that he threw it away. nothing he
होता है उसको उन्होंने फेंका। कुछ नहीं वो
It wasn't burning at all.
वो जल ही नहीं रहा था।
So we had our Kali mantra there
तो हमने जो हमारा काली मंत्र था तो वहीं
of. When our Gurudev said something
का रखा। हमारे गुरुदेव ने बोला था जब कुछ
If you don't have it then you can pick up some soil and perform havan
नहीं आपके पास है तो आप मिट्टी उठाकर हवन
Do it because everything belongs to God. those
कीजिए क्योंकि सब देवता का ही है। उन्हीं
It is made of. That is the five elements. Your
का बना हुआ है। वही पंचमहाभूत है। आपके
Is it all tasty or tasteless for them
लिए स्वाद है या बेस्वाद है उनके लिए सब
That's it. So what did we do that Bhagwati's
वही है। तो हमने क्या किया कि भगवती का
Took the mantra. He picked up the ashes from there and buried them on the pyre
मंत्र लिया। वहीं से राख उठाया और उस चिता
We sacrificed ourselves thrice and that pyre was burnt
में हमने तीन बार आहुति दी और वह चिता जल
got up. So we thought that yes, that means Bhagvati is our
उठी। तो हमें लगा कि हां मतलब भगवती हमारे
and for the first time I realised that
साथ है और पहली बार यह आभास हुआ कि जो
Tantra we are doing or learning
तंत्र हम कर रहे हैं या जो सीख रहे हैं
There is something in it. So it took a lot of time.
उसमें कुछ है। तो इसमें बहुत समय लगा।
Goddess Bhagwati has blessed us very much. very often
बहुत बहुत भगवती ने हमें पटका। बहुत बार
It seemed like I should give up now. Tools
ऐसा लगा कि अब छोड़ देना चाहिए। साधनाएं
We used to do it a lot. in our house our
हम बहुत करते थे। हमारे घर में हमारा जो
The room is at the end and our
कमरा है वो सबसे अंत में है और हमारे
Dad was also about to go to our room at that time.
पिताजी भी हमारे रूम में जाने से उस समय
They were afraid. But then slowly Bhagwati told everything
डरते थे। लेकिन फिर धीरे-धीरे भगवती ने सब
Some things were resolved. Then Tara Mahavidya
कुछ को सुलझा दिया। फिर तो तारा महाविद्या
I. Thara was interviewed in life.
आई। जीवन में थारा का साक्षात्कार हुआ।
Then the eye of knowledge opened. Then Bhairava came. Then
फिर ज्ञान चक्षु खुला। फिर भैरव आए। फिर
The worship of Chin Mastika Baglamukhi Bhairavi
छिन मस्तिका बगलामुखी भैरवी इनका साधना
We did it. Then from the entire Shankaracharya Mahabhag
किया हमने। फिर पूरी शंकराचार्य महाभाग से
We took initiation and then their Bhuvaneshwari
हमने दीक्षा ली और फिर इनका भुवनेश्वरी का
and Tripura Maritime and five Colleges
और त्रिपुरा समुद्री और पांच महाविद्यालय
I practiced his sadhana. That sequence is ongoing right now
उनकी साधना की। अभी चल रहा है वो क्रम चल
Used to be. A friend of mine in my building
रहा है। मेरे बिल्डिंग में मेरे एक फ्रेंड
Is. He found a devi mantra online. And
है। ही फाउंड अ देवी मंत्र ऑनलाइन। और
Asked me to do this. I said yaar I
मुझसे पूछा कि यह करूं। आई सेड यार आई
Don't know honestly. and it's not my right
डोंट नो ऑनेस्टली। एंड इट्स नॉट माय राइट
to give you the meaning because I meant it
टू गिव यू द मतलब बिकॉज़ मैंने यह मतलब
I haven't even practised. we are these
प्रैक्टिस भी नहीं किया है। हम ये जो
I said now it's not my right, is that
मैंने कहा अब कि इट्स नॉट माय राइट इज दैट
The Correct Way of Looking at Things. Yes yes.
द करेक्ट वे ऑफ़ लुकिंग एट थिंग्स। यस यस।
first of all
फर्स्ट ऑफ ऑल
You should get a month from a Guru family. One
यू शुड गेट अ मंथ फ्रॉम अ गुरु परिवार। एक
The mantra should come to you from the guru tradition.
गुरु परंपरा से आपके पास मंत्र आनी चाहिए।
And your Guru has to be given authority by his Guru
और आपके गुरु को उसके गुरु ने अधिकार देना
You should be able to pass on this mantra
होना चाहिए कि आप यह मंत्र आगे दे सकते
Are. Only then are you eligible to cast the spell.
हैं। तभी आप मंत्र करने के लिए वैध है।
Otherwise there are many mantras available. Correct
नहीं तो मंत्र तो बहुत मिल जाते हैं। ठीक
Is? and if you read it you might
है? और अगर आप उसको पढ़ेंगे तो हो सकता है
You may suffer loss. anything can happen to you
आपको हानि हो। हो सकता है आपके साथ कुछ भी
No. Ok? its not good with you
ना हो। ठीक है? अच्छा आपके साथ नहीं हो
Can. Yes. Why can't it happen?
सकता। हां। क्यों नहीं हो सकता है?
Because it is as good as a poem. Or
क्योंकि वो इट इज़ एज गुड एज अ पोएम। या
The mantra of cheating that you don't have the right to
चटिंग का मंत्र जो आपको अधिकार नहीं है वह
It is like a poem. You just read it
एक कविता की तरह है। आप बस पढ़ लीजिए
For him. I told you a story, right
उसको। मैंने एक कहानी बताई थी ना वो
The Englishman who met a saint in Benares
अंग्रेज जो बनारस में एक संत से गया था
To take the Gayatri Mantra. The saint refused
गायत्री मंत्र लेने के लिए। संत ने मना कर
Given that you are English then I am not
दिया कि तुम अंग्रेज हो तो मैं नहीं
Give. The Englishman had money. he is someone
दूंगा। अंग्रेज के पास पैसा था। वो किसी
And went to the Acharya. From that, Gayatri Mantra
और आचार्य के पास गया। उससे गायत्री मंत्र
Took it. He came and told the saint that he had
ले लिया। आकर के संत को बोला कि मेरे पास
This is the Gayatri Mantra. So the saint said you
गायत्री मंत्र है। तो संत ने बोला आप
Recite the Gayatri Mantra. so he heard it from Om
सुनाओ गायत्री मंत्र। तो इसने ओम से सुना
Gave. So the saint recited this Gayatri Mantra
दिया। तो संत ने बोला यह गायत्री मंत्र
Not there. The British thought that we had left. He
नहीं है। अंग्रेज को लगा हम चले गए। वह
He went back to his teacher and said that the saint
वापस गया अपने आचार्य के पास बोला कि संत
I am saying that what you said is
बोल रहे हैं कि आपने जो बोला है यह
There is no Gayatri Mantra. Then Acharya jumped
गायत्री मंत्र नहीं है। तो आचार्य कूद
having done this he came to the saint and said, we have our
करके आए संत के पास और बोला हम आपने हमारे
He told the disciple that this is not the Gayatri Mantra
शिष्य को बोला कि यह गायत्री मंत्र नहीं
Is. So he said no. then he said to the disciple
है। तो बोले नहीं है। तो शिष्य को बोला
tell me. Then the disciple recited the Gayatri
सुनाओ। तो फिर शिष्य ने सुनाया गायत्री
mantra. So you pronounced it literally correct. So
मंत्र। तो शाब्दिक रूप में सही सुनाया। तो
Acharya said this is Gayatri Mantra. Saint
आचार्य ने बोला यही गायत्री मंत्र है। संत
He said this is not Gayatri Mantra. Then
ने बोला यह नहीं है गायत्री मंत्र। फिर
The religious assembly of Banaras met to decide this
बनारस का धर्म सभा बैठा इसका फैसला करने
For and when the religious assembly of Banaras sat
के लिए और जब बनारस का धर्म सभा बैठा ना
Then the Englishman recited the Gayatri Mantra again.
तो अंग्रेज ने फिर से सुनाया गायत्री
The Mantra Dharma Sabha said that he narrated it correctly
मंत्र धर्म सभा ने बोला इसने ठीक सुनाया
The saint said that this is not Gayatri
संत ने बोला कि यह तो नहीं है गायत्री
The religious assembly said the mantra that Saint Sahab
मंत्र तो धर्म सभा ने बोला कि संत महोदय
We too know this Gayatri Mantra
हम लोग भी तो यही गायत्री मंत्र जानते
Are. So he said you guys have the right
हैं। तो उन्होंने बोला आप लोग अधिकार
are received. So when you read this, it
प्राप्त हैं। तो आप जब इसको पढ़िएगा तो यह
This is the Gayatri Mantra. the rights you receive
गायत्री मंत्र है। आप जो अधिकार प्राप्त
he is not a person if he chants the gayatri mantra
व्यक्ति नहीं है वह अगर गायत्री मंत्र
If he reads it then it is not considered as Gayatri
पढ़ता है तो उसको गायत्री नहीं माना
Will go. in the same way if you do anything,
जाएगा। उसी तरीके से आप अगर कुछ भी कोई भी
looking up mantra yantra or tantra online
मंत्र यंत्र या तंत्र ऑनलाइन देख रहे हैं
without any Guru who has the right to
बिना किसी गुरु के जिनको उसका अधिकार ही
If not, then it becomes invalid.
नहीं है तो फिर वो इनवैलिड हो जाता है।
It doesn't make any sense. Then the Psalms
उसका कोई मतलब नहीं रहता है। फिर स्तोत्र
What happens? You can source it.
क्या होता है? स्त्रोत्र आप कर सकते हैं।
All of them are praises, all of them are hymns, all of them
वो सब तो प्रेज़ है ना वो सब हाइम्स वो सब
can you read. Devotion increases. yes joe
आप पढ़ सकते हैं। भक्ति बढ़ती है। हां जो
is a must. Yes. the gods were pleased
बहुत जरूरी है। हां। देवता प्रसन्न होते
It is from him. Like if a normal person is called a goddess
हैं उससे। जैसे अगर नॉर्मल किसी को देवी
If you want to worship then buy Durga Saptashati
उपासना करनी है ना तो दुर्गा सप्तशती खरीद
Take. There is a chapter on Durga in the name of Namaavali
ले। उसमें एक चैप्टर है नामावली का दुर्गा
Durgati Shamani Durga Pad Nivarani Durgham
दुर्गति शमनी दुर्गा पद निवारणी दुर्गम
Chedni Fort Shani Fort Nashani Fort Dhani
छेदनी दुर्ग शाणी दुर्ग नाशनी दुर्ग धणी
Durgani Durmapa Durgam Gyaada Durdaitya
दुर्गणी दुर्मापा दुर्गम ज्ञादा दुर्दैत्य
Lok Dawla Durgama Durmaka Durma
लोक दावला दुर्गमा दुर्माका दुर्मा
Swaroopani Durmap Prada Durgam Vidya
स्वरूपपणी दुर्माप प्रदा दुर्गम विद्या
Durma Durgam Knowledge Institute Durgamani
दुर्मा दुर्गम ज्ञान संस्था दुर्गमनी
Durma Durgamaga Durma Swaroopani Durma
दुर्महा दुर्गमगा दुर्मा स्वरूपणी दुर्मा
Shivshant Durmadharani Durmangi Durmata
शिवशंत दुर्माधारणी दुर्मांगी दुर्मता
Durma Durd Durg Bhima Durbhama Durbha
दुर्मा दुर्द दुर्ग भीमा दुर्भामा दुर्भा
Durdhani has 32 names so this is the name given to it
दुर्धाणी 32 नाम है तो ये जो नाम है इसको
You can chant it every day but you don't have the right
आप रोज जाप कर सकते हैं आपको अधिकार नहीं
Even then you can chant it when you wake up
है तब भी जाप कर सकते हैं आप सोके उठे तब
You can chant this also. Due to this, Bhagwati
भी इसका आप जाप कर सकते हैं। इससे भगवती
She feels very happy. We who worship the Goddess
बहुत प्रसन्न होती है। हम जो देवी उपासक
He can start with this.
है वह शुरुआत इससे कर सकते हैं।
What is the difference then? In which? The mantras and
फर्क क्या होता है फिर? किस में? मंत्र और
In the Psalms. One is a president, right?
स्तोत्रों में। एक तो प्रेज़ है ना वो
It is the grace of Bhagvati that you are like this Bhagvati you
भगवती का प्रज़ है कि आप ऐसी हैं भगवती आप
They are like this. They
ऐसी हैं। वो
It means magnification. That is a prayer. Ok?
मतलब बढ़ाई है। दैट इज़ अ प्रेयर। ठीक है?
And what is the mantra? it's a vibration
और मंत्र क्या है? वो एक वाइब्रेशन है
which the sages and saints had given to us
जिसको ऋषि मुनियों ने हम लोगों के लिए
which has been created by doing it in a correct way
बनाया है जिसको एक सही तरीके से करने से
Our spiritual growth takes place. we are that
हमारा स्पिरिचुअल ग्रोथ होता है। हम तो वो
If it is not done properly it
अगर सही तरीके से नहीं किया गया तो वो
It can also make you imbalanced energy wise
आपको इमंबैलेंस कर सकता है एनर्जी वाइज भी
And mentally too. Great episode.
और मेंटली भी। ग्रेट एपिसोड।
Let's end it here. Ok. it's good
यहीं एंड करते हैं। ठीक है। इट्स गुड
Thoughts for the next one. Ok. and like you
थॉट्स फॉर द नेक्स्ट वन। ओके। और आप जैसे
When people sit on this seat, I need some
लोग जब इस सीट पर बैठते हैं, आई नीड सम
Time off. ok always reflection is needed
टाइम ऑफ। ओके ऑलवेज रिफ्लेक्शन की जरूरत
it occurs. Bhaiya thank you I enjoyed it a lot
होती है। भैया थैंक यू बहुत मजा आ गया एंड
Was waiting for this day again since that day.
वास वेटिंग फॉर दिस डे अगेन सिंस दैट डे।
So hope to do more for Bharat with you. sure
तो होप टू डू मोर फॉर भारत वि यू। श्योर
Thank you. Good luck. Thank you so much. Hello.
थैंक यू। गुड लक। थैंक यू सो मच। नमस्कार।
So friends, this was today's episode. Just like that
तो दोस्तों ये था आज का एपिसोड। ऐसे ही
Spiritual episodes will continue to be released.
स्पिरिचुअल एपिसोड्स रिलीज होते रहेंगे।
And if you liked this episode:
एंड अगर आपको यह वाला एपिसोड अच्छा लगा तो
Definitely prequel episode which Sushir bhai
डेफिनेटली प्रीक्वल एपिसोड जो सुशीर भाई
That episode was also recorded with
के साथ रिकॉर्ड हुआ था वो वाला एपिसोड भी
Consume it. I will link it below.
कंज्यूम करें। उसे नीचे लिंक कर देंगे।
TRS and the full team will be back very soon
टीआरएस एंड द फुल टीम विल बी बैक वेरी
Listen. Thank you for listening in.
सून। थैंक यू फॉर लिसनिंग इन।
[music]
[संगीत]
yes
हो